<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An embassage from the kings of the east to His Highness the Lord Protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</title>
            <author>W. B. (William Blake), fl. 1650-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12966</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11829156</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11829156</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28345)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 809:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An embassage from the kings of the east to His Highness the Lord Protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</title>
                  <author>W. B. (William Blake), fl. 1650-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4, 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Blake. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49710:1"/>
            <p>AN EMBASSAGE FROM THE KINGS of the EAST TO HIS HIGHNES THE Lord Protector Of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed in the year 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49710:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49710:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſoul of man, the glories of the world, are never ſitting face to face, nor ſide by ſide, much leſſe reſt they as in one bed, but are ever looking like the Eaſt and Weſt one from another, and although in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture they ſeem to be coupled, it is but by the thred of life, which every little diſtemper, years, age or cauſualty ſnaps aſunder, tumbling both as in one moment wider from each other; than is the Sun and ſhadow, nor are theſe, the ſoul of man, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the world ſtanding ſtill, or reſting in this preſent poſture, back to back, but like to penny birds upon a painted board, are alwayes dopping down the head, and picking one another; ſure I am the ſoul, thrice noble and immortal may pick and, peck for in this flattering-world, honours, glories, joyes and pleaſures in a greedy way, but theſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures dig down faſt and ſoon this glory, yea God, I was about to ſay, the ſoul of man, or breath of his, yea they dig down that as low as hell, and in a moments time all your dayes, my Lord, are no more, nor are they that, compared with eternity;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49710:3"/> if the heavens be but as the wearing of a garment out, what is then the life of man but as the putting on or off? yea the glance of it, much leſs are all his wants, fears, hopes, joyes and glories.</p>
            <p>O my ſoul, flee away from all theſe things, be at reſt, yea, at work, if there be time and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in thy hand, to do for God, ſelf, ſouls, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Why ſhould eternity drop upon thee, or thou roul into it before thou art aware? Do what thou wilt; dye and get thee hence to thine own place, come no more here, men are plotting, God prevents, the mourners go about the ſtreet, but the Spirit to him that gave it, Go, Welldone, Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours my</hi> LORD, WILL. BLAKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49710:3"/>
            <head>To the whole Iſrael of GOD greeting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hurches, Saints and Chriſtians, a true lover of you all in all forms, ſcarce known, or worthy ſo to be, Dedicates this little Book or labour of love to you and your acceptance, yea proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, which be who will, firſt and moſt in, they are the glory of the world Kings, Shepherds, Star, and Angel lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men to Chriſt, or rather ſhowing where they have laid by him and his truth, all which may be done as followeth, if you proſecute this buſineſſe to the life, not loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one day, and how many brave deſigns have failed for want of that? O let it never be ſaid, every man mindeth his own things and none the things of Chriſt; you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe much, many of you do ſo, but who layes by all a little while for him? yea, who makes it his whole and ſole buſineſſe to advance his Name, Fame, Kingdom and glory in the world, he is not ſo far gone but he will come again, <hi>Asts</hi> 1. 11. yea, as
<pb facs="tcp:49710:4"/> a thief in the night, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 15. and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is with him. Watch for the good man of the houſe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. 35. and know if he did know of the thiefs coming, he would certainly prepare and not ſleep like the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Virgins, do not you as do thoſe who are of the night, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2. you are of the day walk as the children of the light, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the time, becauſe the dayes are evill, bleſſed is he that keeps his garments unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, and is not found beating of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, but walking with his lamp burning like a beacon, but who almoſt does ſo, or mindes that Chriſt to any purpoſe, who wills, longs, loves, yea, crowns us with his own glory the glory of the Father, and ſets us in his throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 21. his work we are at, and recommend it unto you, but if it ſtick, let it lye in the day of account up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his account that ſhall ſlight it, ſaying, I am not concerned, I am not at leiſure, and I am not well, ſatisfied how, when, and what it is you would be at; well you may ſhuffel cut and put it off to one another as much as you pleaſe, but it wil be hardly anſwered one day, and it may begrieve you when tis too late, that the beſt of you all have
<pb facs="tcp:49710:4"/> done no more for him in your preſent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; do not ſit piping or lamenting, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 17. things may do well enough for all this; what need we care who rules, ſo Chriſt reigns and his Saints, which are beſt at Prayer and Preaching, if we have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to purpoſe, for the latter let us be content in the Name of God, elſe never whilſt we breath, yea, without this let our tongues rot, and cleave unto our mouths rather then be ſilent, but mannage well that, it is enough for <hi>Peter, Paul, Iames, Iack or Iohn</hi> and the poor Saints ſo to do, our turn will be next, and our day is a coming, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Iud.</hi> 14. what would <hi>Ionas, Iob, Iacob,</hi> and the reſt of good men do but for one Chriſt, whom, who almoſt mindes, knowes, loves or likes, he is ſo poor, mean, low far off, ſlow and long of coming to do any thing for one or the other; but when he comes it is to purpoſe, his reward will be with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 12. In the mean time we leave his work with you Churches, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Saints and others, the Spirit bid us do it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, and every one of yours, in the neereſt bonds. <hi>W. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:49710:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>And the last beaſt was like a flying Eagle.</hi> Rev. 4. 7. Such a Spirit ſhould be now in all the Saints, this being the laſt age of the world.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Let all write with this Quill, other Pens are out of date in this knowing age.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49710:5"/>
            <head>An Embaſſage from the Kings of the Eaſt, To His Highneſſe the LORD PROTECTOR <hi>of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y LORD PROTECTOR, in the Name of God Almighty, we the poor unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of your Lord and Maſter do with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in love, zeal, and humility, Petition you and your Honourable Councel for our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> purchaſed by the blood of Chriſt, made over in his Word, and witneſſed by his Spirit to be our true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right, more than the blood of our veines; but the great enemy of Mankinde, the Devil, and his tail, the Pope and the popiſh Cleargy have robbed us this many years, not of health, wealth or lives, but our Charter, our deereſt Charter, our Chriſtian Liberty purchaſed as beforeſaid, but yet withheld. O my Lord, this is our caſe, and a ſad one it is, that we redeemed by Chriſt, muſt thus be bound by men; had we never known our Liberty, we would not now complain, nor this day mourn for it, but now our harps are on the Willowes, nor can we ſing the ſongs of Sion, nor her deliverance fully come, whilſt we are ſtill in this captivity, and freed from all almoſt beſides, but may you live to ſet your hand to them whoſe hearts are yet with you, as <hi>Jonathans</hi> was with <hi>David,</hi> froward things are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in our mouths, yet our hearts can never be divorc'd, nor our affections let go you out of our thoughts; no, no, my Lord, far be that ingratitude from us, who long ſince have learned better things, and as far be it from you to forget us, who were once as deer to you almoſt as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to <hi>Paul,</hi> for whom he even wiſht himſelf accurſt, jeapordi'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49710:6"/> his life a thouſand times, hunger, cold and perils, ſure the latter you have done, &amp; more than ever any did, &amp; that for us a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring people againſt you, and your God, whoſe protection with you &amp; the Iſrael of God under your command, was your guard &amp; rearguard, yea your ſtrength &amp; victory in all your migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty battels in every nation: Oh that we ſhould do ſo, &amp; oh that we ſhould be ſo unworthy, ſo illy to requit ſo good a God, ſo good a ſervant, it is our ſin, let never yours be to revenge, or yet be angry with a froward people, it was <hi>Moſes</hi> ſin, you know his puniſhment, far be that from you, may you ſee the deliverance of Sion fully wrought, and they, as in the land of promiſe, all the priveledges of the Goſpel, yea this may you ſee in your dayes, and ſay in the end thereof, <hi>Let me now thy ſervant depart in peace, ſo mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation,</hi> the ſalvation of Sion, and her deliverance ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought, and oh that your ſoul with ſuch expreſſions may leave this world at once; this flattering world, whoſe higheſt glories, joyes and pleaſures leaves but ſadneſſe in the ſoul of man, yea, they fill that immortall Jewell with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but ſhame, guilt and ſorrow, but may your Sun ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſet in ſuch clouds, but like a rain-bow in a hopefull day; This is our Prayer, and now comes our Petition, not for our lives nor our liberties commonly ſo called, but our Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian Priviledge yet not granted to us, no, nor ſcarce thought on neither; My Lord excuſe us, we cannot but with hearts grief ſo ſpeak it, care is taken for many things, we doubt not, the poor, the fatherleſſe, the right of the needy, the debts, Lawes and Liberties of the Nation, as far as this jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of time will give leave, yea further, the Goſpel, and the Preaching of the Goſpel by godly ſound and able men, with the diſcountenance of all vice and unſoundneſſe: And yet my Lord, is this all? far be it from you to think ſo; we look, we long, we hope for more; yea, for more than all this, and never ſhall be ſilent, till you, or your God and ours hear: We look, we long for liberty in our ſelves whilſt men have it in their thoughts to cruſh us for owning Chriſt too much, and yet it is too little, yea this is the thing we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49710:6"/> tend the throne of grace for now, whilſt we petition you, and the godly in your Councel for Liberty in our ſelves, for the word is as fire in our bones, the Spirit having long ſince kindled it, we cannot longer now be ſilent, but do claime for this as our undoubted Priviledge, Namely the exerciſe of our Gifts in the open Congregations; yea, this is ſo much our duty, and a Priviledge, that we cannot without guilt, ſin, and ſhame keep one moment longer ſilent, no, no, it is too long ſince we have wrong'd our ſelves, our choyceſt ſelves this way, and grieved the Spirit to purpoſe; yea, we have wrong'd thouſands as our ſelves, had our candle been as on a hill, which is as underneath a buſhell, how many ſouls might we ere this day have enlightned, ſome of which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily are in hell complaining of their unhappineſſe and our unfaithfulneſſe. My Lord, this is the caſe, and it is plain and clear, we are guilty, we are guilty in the preſence of the LORD; yea, we confeſſe before heaven, earth, men and Angels, and all the hoſte of both we are guilty, and what ſhall we now do, but with ropes about our necks, guilt ſhame and ſorrow in our ſouls now about our work, and oh that the the time is ſo far paſt, and we not aware; but the night comes on wherein no man can work<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for God, Chriſt, ſelf, or others; yet that we may at laſt be doing to purpoſe, yea for all men.</p>
            <p>My Lord, we cry for help, and cry we will untill delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance come by you, or elſe ſome other way; <hi>Iſrael</hi> was heard, &amp; we doubt not but we ſhall be the like, our cauſe is far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we groan not for outward burdens (though ſome do and that juſtly too, but for the glorious liberty of the Sons of God; yea, to be ſet into that by you, &amp; O my Lord <hi>Crumwel,</hi> now under God our Protector; if you ſhall ſay the time is not yet come, and defer us one moment longer, God will lay you by, and certainly out of the hearts of his deereſt ones, and raiſe up deliverance ſome other way, for the time of Sions deliverance is come, &amp; will come, let men and divels ſay nay, yea the ſet time is come, and the watchmen are on her walls, there they ſee it, and the Spirit of Propheſie is in their mouths, and they will not keep ſilent longer, you are to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49710:7"/> guard them that is your Title, work and Honour, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of Nations, without the affections of Gods people, is a ſmall thing; your greatneſſe glory and honour is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if while you ſit at the ſtern you guide not the ſhip for the moſt to Gods glory, the good of his people, and ſouls of all men, how much will this tend to both; yea, to the Nations of which we may with ſadneſſe ſay millions periſh for want of knowledge, thouſands have words in their mouths, abilities, with ſincerity in their hearts, why ſhould they want incouragement, or rather protection by a law for that ſame purpoſe; for that is all they do deſire, a ſmall thing for you, my Lord, to deny to them.</p>
            <p>Let them be tryed, and tryed again, and again, for ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſoundneſſe, holineſſe and ability in ſome meaſure, the latter will come on apace, when we have this Liberty, Protection and Commiſſion to ſpeak in all the ſchooles of the Prophets and Churches of Chriſt, the national ones. In all which we promiſe by the grace of God, whoſe we are, to do nothing againſt the truth, but for it, waving all diſputes, and contentions whatſoever, nothing in diſdain to our Fathers in Chriſt, but in love to our brethren and ſiſters, eſpecially the little ones, yea for their ſakes plead we thus, and the ſtrangers that knowes not God; but you will ſay they are taught already, true, my Lord, and better then we can do it, yet we will not rob them nor unteach them, but add a word of our experience in convenient ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſometimes ſooner, ſometimes later; This was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by your Army to the good of thouſands in their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches up and down, yea the greateſt my Lord, you know it well enough, the publick exerciſes are as the bellowes of the Almighty on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s people, carried on in the Spirit, their hearts being warmed with the breath thereof, might not they then add a word or two of their experience; O how ſweet would that be from the ſence of Gods love ſo to do, one hour before or after would fit us for, or faſten thoſe things which now too ſoon we looſe, thus might we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, how ſweet and lovely would the Aſſemblies of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49710:7"/> people be, yea, how primitive like then would all our deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt brethren return again never more to ſeparate from us, but would be as lamps and pillars in our Aſſemblies? And why may not theſe Jewels, and their Luſtre ſhine as well there as where few reſort.</p>
            <p>O my Lord, bring them forth that have lyen among the pots, they will be as doves whoſe feathers are covered with yellow gold; yea let the world ſee, the gifts and graces of the ſonnes of Sion more precious than choice ſilver, ſay unto them upon whom the glory of the Lord is riſen, ariſe and ſhine, for their feet are beautifull, and their God will be admired; yea then will Satan and his Kingdom fall like lightening before the Spirit of the Lord, men will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the Saints, nor periſh for want of knowledge, as now they doe, whilſt they think they have as much as any, not knowing what the Saints through grace doe; then will the boules of the Temple be uſefull indeed, other men have laid them by, but bring them you out, that every one may drink from their experience the waters of life, &amp; receive the bread of life, for that is that we promiſe now to break, and nothing of ſelf, further be it from us ever to broach ſchiſm, faction, treaſon, or rebellion; yea, any thing more than one thing our Lord Jeſus Chriſt his loves and lovelineſs, yea nothing but faith, Chriſt, his righteouſneſſe, healing, and practicall points, we promiſe to preach nothing elſe but theſe things, and the humility of Chriſt for our example, nor will we ever ſlight thoſe ſtars that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed us firſt to him: no, no, they that travelled with us, and pointed out the Lamb of God before us, ſhall never be forgotten if they will be quiet; they are our Fathers, and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wel of double honor, yea we will ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did to <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, my Lord, our old Friend, and good Friend, will you hear, will you help us your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llow members once again in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k of time, why ſhould others have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from you, try and try us by whom you pleaſe, yea, ſet up ſuch as may do it, and the God of heaven ſet up you in the hearts of his. My Lord, we fear not the touch;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49710:8"/> many will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t though moſt are not ſo in any meaſure, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them be unbyaſſed, not all of the Cleargy, and try us while they will, they will find men enough; we deſire not to run, before ſo ſent by you or they, nor then out of our calling to the charge of the Nation, but here and there as Providence leads to witneſſe for the Truth, moſt in our Pariſhes where our walking is known.</p>
            <p>O my Lord, this were Chriſtian liberty indeed, this were to be freed from Antichriſt to purpoſe. Men talk as if after all we ſhould go back again, far be that from the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, and as far be it from you to withhold your hand from this work of his, give us this Jewell long loſt, make up this breach, and give us liberty as in the dayes of old, and then we will lift up our heads, yea voices, and ſing together, yea we will never more complain, but ſing the ſongs of Sion, and her deliverance fully come, and under God and Chriſt you ſhall have the glory, yea, the glory of all we are or have in this particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> hath ſlain his thouſands and <hi>David</hi> his ten thouſands, ſo have you, but <hi>Solomon</hi> built the Temple, and ſo have you, when theſe tryed ſtones are laid in every place; yea, you have then done more for Chriſt, the Saints, the World, the Souls of men, than all the Chriſtian Kings and Princes that ever was; none has had a heart, nor none has had a hand for this, nor none are in memory of Saints to purpoſe, but you ſhall be for ever; yea let our tongues cleave to the roofe of our mouthes, if we forget your labour of love in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; yea though we or ſome of us have railed at you; yea prayed to blaſt you in your late Proceedings, yet will we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g you in our boſomes, and ſay you are more righteous than thouſands.</p>
            <p>To wind up all, you know our mindes, conſult not with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſh and blood, nor byaſſed men; The Lord Jeſus and his Spirit hold you cloſe to the rule, keep you waking night by night on your bed to weigh our Petition, and if it be right hear us, as ever he ſhould hear you in your heart-ſick-dying hour, when you and this world muſt part.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49710:8"/>
            <p> O my Lord, hear us, we are his, though all of his are not with us, yet thouſands are, and why, and how can be againſt us, the Word and Spirit is for us; yea God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: My ſons and my daughters ſhall Propheſie, be not you againſt us; n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d none but you can hinder, yea, againſt him who hath been your ſalvation all along, yea and them too, which at your command have ſhed blood, and loſt blood life limbes, and relations, yea, and all upon this account, more than any.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> never fought with <hi>Amalek</hi> on ſo low account as pay, nor we with our neighbours for vineyards, ſhadows, and titles; no, no, let it never be ſaid in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſtreets of <hi>Askalum,</hi> here or in other countries, we deſtroyed towns, cities fired houſes, ſpilt the blood of mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, and ſent ſouls to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, ſo low account; one valley ful of ſculs and bones are more worth than theſe, beſides, former vowes would be minded, and in this the main is paid, death would be minded, and for this you may take comfort, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be minded, and for this you may expect a Crown, if for any work under heaven.</p>
            <p>O my Lord, to have a Crown from Chriſt, with this ſaying, Weldone and Welcome, when Kings and Captains ſhall run to the rocks, <hi>hills and mountains.</hi> This is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, may ſuch conſiderations ever well in great ment hearts, and flatterers far from all your Councels, for if you ſhould miſcarry, good had it been if you had never been, or any thing but what you are; The Name of Chriſt, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, the expectation of the Saints, the eyes of all the nations round about are more on you than any man on earth, the Lord God Almighty, and the Prayers of his People lead you and your Councel in all wayes of well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49710:9"/>
            <p> LEt us now treat a little with the people of the Nation, I mean common Proteſtants, that do confeſſe Chriſt, and that is all, and me thinks we hear moſt of them rail, laugh, and jear others, judging and condemning us for proud fooles and hypocrites, and ſuch, as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et alone will ſpoil the Church in time; wiſe men would weep to ſee mad men laugh, and as much laugh to hear fools rail, for their Miniſters, and they know not what; well, curſe, rail, jear, and do what you will, we are ſtill the ſame, yea ſuch as do truly pity and pray for you, though you cannot for your ſelves, nor will not ſo well as you may; the Lord Jeſus do both for you, and open your eyes to ſee and loath what you love, and love what you l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath, eſpecially the people of God, ſome of which you would ſend for, if you were to die with ſpeed; fetch them, fetch them, let them come &amp; pray; well, now you have them, do not rail, that is diviliſh, nor judge them that is preſumption, or leave your Churches if they ſhould come there to exerciſe their Gifts, they, time and your preſent meanes of grace will too ſoon be gone: if they ſpeak of their experiences, they have learned ſomething: if they ſpeak of Chriſt the love, and lovelines of Chriſt, <hi>(Eph.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 16.) then it ſeems they know him, and that it <hi>life eternall, John</hi> If they ſpeak of ſin the ſinfulneſſe of that, then it ſeems they loath it, if they ſpeak of you and the way to heaven, they would ſave you from the wayes to hell, which we are ſure you are in, if you loath them for their love to God, Chriſt, his Word, and your ſouls; one of which is more worth than a thouſand worlds, and although it be your own proper work and the Miniſters to minde that, yet are we in conſcience bound not to ſuffer ſin upon your heads; who would not help an ox out of the pit <hi>(Mat.</hi> 12. 11.) if like to periſh? Much more a ſoul, they that this way ſet thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> helping hands can never be your enemies, God forbid that theſe lamps ſhould be ſo counted, though they be not torches, leſſer lights may be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49710:9"/> uſeful, ſo may the gifts &amp; graces of the Saints, the Spirit ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where it liſteth, <hi>John</hi> 3. 8. Hear that where ever it be. Would a ſoul in hell ſay, If I were on earth I would not hear the Saints, or ſhould a man for heaven ſay, I wil go no further, ſuch &amp; ſuch are going too, ô Friend, if you be going to hell, or they be going to heaven, hear &amp; conſider before it be too late, time wil never come again, nor they nor you from the dead to hear one another, now you have <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets, <hi>Luk.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. 31. ſo are they whom ye deſpiſe, if they preach to you the ſame trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, by the ſame Spirit, the Lord make you wiſe, after wit will do no good, nor repentance neither one day you may ſay, O that we had the Saints again, their prayers light, and Counſels, when it is too late; A certain man, where ſome of theſe lay priſoners in the late warres, thought of them as ſome of you now do, but he being ſick to death, cryed night and day, fetch the Saints again, fetch the Saints again, but they were gone long before; be the Sun-ſet or near it; you are they dead or dying; what will good Sun, good death, or good Saint, ſtay a little longer? Any thing avail? No, no, the night comes and none can work, <hi>John</hi> 9. 3. they for you, nor you for your ſelves Let them preach, let them ſpeak, let them pray while they may, if they be againſt your ſins, they are for your ſouls, if they be againſt your cuſtomes the old or the new, it is for a better, may not time before and after Miniſters have done be better ſpent then it is, eſpecially the Lords day, and the after part of it, but you are afraid your Religion will go down, take heed that that be not a form rather than a truth, many have the form of godlineſſe, but deny the power, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. But the bulk of men deny both in <hi>England;</hi> Lord, what ſhould be the cauſe; have our Paſtors made us ſo, nuſling us up in ignorance, <hi>My people periſh for want of knowledge, ſayeth the Lord, Prov.</hi> 29. 28. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4 6. And ſayeth Chriſt <hi>If the blinde lead the blinde,</hi> wo be to both, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 39. or have you oppoſed truth, and would not ſee the light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your deeds, <hi>John</hi> 3 19. Searching light is a ſaving light, if well improved; have your Miniſters ſo preached as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49710:10"/> certainly many have, take heed that you refuſe not him that ſpeaks from heaven <hi>(Heb.</hi> 12. 25.) by their mouths yea, and take heed of winking at what you ſee or may ſee in guifted Chriſtians, they can tell you from experience in their own language the mercies of a God, <hi>(Eph.</hi> 3. 18.) the heighth, depth, breadth and length, yea, to you the worſt of ſinners, if you will accept it, but I obtained mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. Yea they can tell you of his Loves, the length and ſtrength of that in ſome meaſure, which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than life, ſo ſayeth <hi>David. Pſal.</hi> 63. 3.</p>
            <p>This love and mercy God ſends to ſinners ſometimes by poor, weak, plain and unworthy men, without Latine Phraſes, therefore thouſands do refuſe it, yea, Chriſt the Bread, the Tree, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 7. the Well of life <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 36. 9.) is the like with all his Loves, lovelineſs and vertues, <hi>(Luk</hi> 6. 19) upon the ſame account.</p>
            <p>O Chriſt, who almoſt knowes thee? Who almoſt owns thee, <hi>the chiefeſt of ten thouſand? Cant.</hi> 5. 10. which art all in all in life, death, and eternity, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 11. Well, this King, Prieſt and Prophet can the Saints tell the world of, yea by the Spirit in the Word, they can open as it were his ſide and heart, give them out his blood, to ſet their ſouls free from ſin, death, hell and eternall burnings, yea they can give a taſte of the life and joyes to come, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 3. one drop thereof is more worth than the treaſures of the world, if well conſidered, yea they can breath upon you the holy Ghoſt, my meaning is, they by the Spirit in them breathing from them, conveyes the words of life to poor ſinners many times; thouſands can ſeal to this; no fires ever kindled one another like this ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y fire: the Spirit of love, the Dove in <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. 8. reſt it where it will it ever brings an embleme of peace from the God of peace.</p>
            <p>O that men ſhould refuſe this love, this Dove, this peace, an embleme of peace ſpeckled with the blood of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it breatheth not where the world liſteth, but it ſelf, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 8.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49710:10"/>
            <p> Well, be ye not offended, I go not to throw down men nor Miniſters, no, the Lord Jeſus keep up them that are good and watch for your ſouls as they that muſt give account for in the day of judgement, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. and throw down all, yea all beſides, and what I ſay for Miniſters, who are your Seer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. 10. Prophets, Watchmen, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 19. Shepherds, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 4. which have the main care of your ſouls commited <hi>(Acts</hi> 20. 28.) to them by Chriſt, when as he ſends them to you, and not a leſſer benefice; the ſame I ſay for gifted Brethren, Saints by calling and Profeſſion, the Lord increaſe their number, gift them, and give them more favour in your eyes, not for their ſakes, but your own: theſe are neither Watchmen nor Shepherds extraordinary in an outward call, yet ar they all inwardly, ſo if gifted &amp; bound by God, reaſon and nature to do you all the good they can; yea, they muſt preach to you by life and doctrine, as <hi>Noah</hi> and Lot to the old world, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. yea, they are bound to pray for you by night and day, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1. and as they are bound by God and Nature to do this for you, ſo are you by Scripture-bonds and common ingenuity to love their perſons, and minde their Counſels, and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome admonitions, and wo to he that ſhall ſtorm againſt it or Phariſie-like grieve at this kind of doctrine, Well, take heed ye reſiſt not the holy Ghoſt, <hi>(Acts</hi> 7. 51.) nor fight againſt the mind of God, from ignorance of his word, much more like <hi>Shimei</hi> to rail and curſe good <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 7. I mean good men for nothing but pointing out the lamb of God in <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſts abſence, <hi>(John</hi> 1. 35.) or preſence either; if it be he they point at, as certainly they do, look for the objects ſake, that takes away the ſins of the world, and that by your looking on him the true braſen Serpent, which every man ſhould labour to ſet-up, <hi>John</hi> 3. 14.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49710:11"/>
            <head>A Warning-Meſſage, or a Parley with the Miniſters.</head>
            <p>OF all good men on earth, your godly Miniſters are the beſt, that are really ſo, and ſelf deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men: the moſt good they do, they are to us as the rivers to the valleys, they make us by Gods bleſſing fruitful in good wayes and works, yea they make us through perſwaſion of the Spirit loath the world, and love God, yea all of God, and all of good, they bring down God to us, and us to God by Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they charm us with the loves of Chriſt, and wooes us by the Spirit to make a match with him, who is the chiefeſt of ten thouſand, and altogether lovely, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 10. They raiſe us from the death of ſin, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. and yet we die again, yea dayly to the world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 13. They lift us up, they lay us low, yea at the gates of hell, by ſhowing us our ſins, and by a word of faith they raiſe us again, by lifting up the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Serpent, <hi>John</hi> 3 yea when we are like the Sallamander in the flames of afflictions, they make us ſing like the Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale, by ſhowing the good of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 28. the loves of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 19. yea with the Spirits aſſiſtance, they can do any thing for us, or with us. but without that they can do nothing, ſo that it is God alone that doth all, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 13. and yet what he uſually doth is by them, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6,) inſtrumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ally, he wins, ſaves and comforts ſouls, yea the moſt loſt and afflicted ones, and ſo they are the beſt of men in one ſence, and do the moſt good whilſt others harden they ſoften, others lead to the pit, and deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction, yea, ſome Miniſters be witch men with a form in ſtead of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49710:11"/> ſubſtance, and that a poor empty one too, how many have nothing elſe but old empty nothing ſtufe from their Paſtors, yea ſcarce moral things, Law nor Goſpel never heard, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, nor can many hundreds diſtinctly preach either the new birth, the new Creator, the gifts of God, the graces of the Spirit, how to comfort or caſt down, they know no more then the plowman doth the Planets, ſuch kind of men we loath, not their perſons but their ſin, in taking to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves this high and holy calling, the proper Names of it, Chriſts Ambaſſadors they are, and they know not how to treat about the ſouls of men and heavenly things, who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and who not, never making any diſtinction in praying or preaching to any purpoſe, theſe Prieſts never of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd one ſacrifice all their dayes for themſelves, nor thoſe poor ſouls upon whom they live and feed their family on, yea feed bare: if a horſe be ridden with a hag, he will never thrive, ſome ſay, if a man or a Parriſh be the like (as too many be in <hi>England)</hi> with ſuch a kind of Prieſt they and their ſouls can never thrive, no, it is impoſſible; thoſe ſet up will ſurely look to this before they put down us that are gifted, can the fiſh live without water, the beaſt without food, or the ſouls of men without ſomething, and where nothing is, nothing can be had; empty Preaching, praying with a little Popery, and Latine, pleaſes poor country men for preſent, but dambs them in the end, yea, and ſome in the City too, elſe they would never run to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rybone</hi> and <hi>Paddington,</hi> and up and down to many places more in the City, where the old ſaints meet for a lick of Antichriſt, yea the very tail of him, but let us leave theſe ſnuffes and old Prieſts, time may put them out for all their preſent hopes, and a little treat with our Fathers the godly Miniſters, and for them we are not ſick, unleſſe it be for more, and yet amongſt them fair dealing is not uſed; they would not be intrencht upon as they themſelves do upon us and our Liberties, yea our fathers do ſo, yet you cry out we have too much, we cry out we have too little, and not without cauſe, eſpecially now, when it is in your thoughts to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49710:12"/> take what we have from us, what means the jerks this way in moſt of your Sermons, if it be not ſo; well, rob us, if you pleaſe, get what you can; in the mean time know we are for Chriſtian Liberty, the exerciſe of our gifts in the ſame places before or after you, for we ſay, they that have hands muſt work, and they that have gifts muſt the like, again ſo to do is a great advantage to our ſouls and others, and we are bound to do good to all men in an outward way, much more to the ſouls of one another, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10. we muſt not receive the grace of God in vain, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1. which we do as to others, when we do not improve our gifts and graces; again according to what is given will be required of every man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 16, 23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 15, 16. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Let every man as he hath received the gift administer the ſame one to another, as good diſpoſers of the manifold graces of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
            <p>Weigh theſe Scriptures well; and ſee if we be to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved for what we claim as our Priviledge and duty; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain conſider whether by the Word, the people of God are any where reproved for exerciſing of their gifts, or were they ever checkt for it, before Antichriſt crept into the world, the Word holds out that if we have any ſpeciall gifts or parts, we muſt exerciſe them as may be moſt for the uſe of the Church, and the Spirit of God, it ſeems to be given us for this very purpoſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 6, 7. again is it not Propheſied we ſhal be able ſo to do, <hi>Joel.</hi> 2. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 16. 1 <hi>John</hi> 46. 13. Is not this Spirit that thus dwels in us a teaching Spirit as well as a pleading, or a preaching Spirit as wel as a praying; yea are not we bid to covet and deſire that it may be ſo.</p>
            <p>Minde thoſe Texts wel, and give a Sermon on one of them if you dare at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 1, 5, 30. but ye are all of you to ſhie this way, yea I think ſcarce any of you good, men, that can freely ſay as Moſes, <hi>Num.</hi> 11. 29. <hi>I would all the Lords people were Prophets,</hi> and with <hi>Paul, I rejoice that Chriſt is preached, though it be of ill will, Phil.</hi> 1. 15, 15. But you grieve although we preach Chriſt of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49710:12"/> good will, judge us to be ſelfiſh, proud, and ſelf-conceited, the Lord pardon, we do, and in his preſence profeſſe, what we do we do in love and obedience, though you ſay in pride; the Word of Chriſt, which we preach thus in good will, ſeems to be committed to our care and charge as well as yours; <hi>Contend earneſtly for the faith (Jude</hi> 3.) once delivered to the Saints, that is the doctrine of the Scripture which we are to diſpute, pray and preach up; you tell us of <hi>Corah, Dathan, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi>'s, ſtaying of the Ark, 1 Chron. and would fain frighten us from the Work of God: What things the people were forbidden, they might not do, but what we are commanded we may and muſt do, and we are bid to build up one another, pray with and for one another, admoniſh and Propheſie to one another, yea all Propheſie one by one, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 31. meaning not in an extraordinary way, but in an ordinay way of opening Scriptures, Propheſies and Promiſes to one another, you tell and fright us with what men were forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to do, we tell you of what we are bidden and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, thou ſhalt not ſuffer ſin upon thy brothers head, but come, ye and tell us what judgement did befall upon <hi>Apolos,</hi> or <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> and <hi>Aquilla</hi> that preached unto him, <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 26, 28. Pray, tell us if you can, in the next, the meaning of this Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 24. But you object and cry out, this kinde of Doctrine, and if all might preach will fill the Church with Errors; from whence comes that? Chriſt is of another mind, <hi>Math.</hi> 22. 29. We are called, not you, ſayes the Preachers, to one place and people; in an outward way they are ſo; yea ſome to two or three, but that we know no warrant for, nor well which flock they are charged withall, we are not with any, not is it our duty to make it our whole buſineſſe as it is yours, and not to write newes, make ſtrife, accuſe us to, or the Magiſtrates to us, you ſay, the Prieſts lips were to preſerve knowledge, now the Spirit is poured out upon the people, breaths in and from the people; this is a better help to us then the gift of tongues, <hi>The Spirit ſearcheth all things yea</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49710:13"/> 
               <hi>the deep things of God,</hi> and that learning cannot, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. yea this Spirit leads us into all truth, when men leads us by many times, but here comes in the great one: If ye preach, ye will baptize in a little while; No, no, we deny that, and it may be are not for it as you are, or the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Churches either, more of Mr. <hi>Dells</hi> judgement the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Baptiſm, but we think, ſome of us thinks ſo, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers may break bread together, though it be moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for a Paſtor and Preacher in office, yea the dead may bury the dead, and who will unleſſe he be a fat hog or rich Saint, yea, the beſt Text in the Bible is ſcarce good enough for either this in practice you alow; and now cryes ſome we will have no Preachers at all within a little while, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid we ſhould ſay ſo: and yet will we bake, brew and dreſſe meat for our ſelves, yet do we not deſtroy the Trades nor your peculiar calling in all that we ſtand for, nor do we ever intend to ſet it up more then he, the profeſſion of a Lawyer that ſtudieth the Lrwes for the good of himſelf, and ſome few friends, or many for whom he freely pleads now and then, but you like not that neither.</p>
            <p>Well, we have hinted at our judgement as well as we can in a ſheet or two, and what have we ſaid to offend you, ourſelf denying godly Paſtors, truly nothing we ſhould think, but now happily we may, and yet we will hide our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers nakedneſſe with the mantle of modeſty, minding our diſtance; you cry out for our affections, we for our affliction, yea all of us for our Liberty: the truth is, you rob us and chide us, but looſers beſt may ſpeak, you cry out for honour, we freely give you, double, our dutie it is, and yours to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in the Word of Chriſt, withholding nothing of his minde from us, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 27. But however ſee you be <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſts ſelf-denying men, <hi>John</hi> 3 30. and ſuch as give all your glorie to Chriſt, owning his Members and the gifts of his Spirit every where, and God will give you honour: <hi>He that honours me, him will my father honour, John</hi> 12. 26. yea and all the Saints too.</p>
            <p>Again, would you honour us now and then in our meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49710:13"/> where we may erre, and do what we pleaſe for all you we ſhould honour you more in your Pulpits: yea this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion would bring the world to a love and liking of the Saints Aſſemblings, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25. which now they throw dirt on: you not commending them ſo much as in your Pulpits, but revile them, too often you cry out of Errors, more then needs many times, yet too many are we do confeſſe: but to put the Divel, Pope, Jeſuites, Anabaptiſts, Antinomians together, meaning Goſpel Miniſters, I think, as a great Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Miniſter lately did in his Prayer, then cryed out, the Lord confound the deſignes of them all, or worſe ſeems ſomething bitter, and why might not liberty be given to object in ſuch a caſe without offence, Sermon being ended, you would weigh the more what you ſometimes pray and preach: yee too often read from a Paper, and we grieve the leſſe when we hear ſuch kind of things, but we will wind up all leſt we ſhould offend too much where we love &amp; honour.</p>
            <p>Our requeſt is in the name of Chriſt our Lord and yours, that ye would be faithful in this controverſal points, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in truth our deſires be according to the minde of God, as certainly they are for the glory of his Name, the exaltation of his Son and Spirit, and againſt ſin and Satans Kingdom, wicked men, divels, and the works of darkneſſe: yea, if it be againſt ignorance the mother ſin of the Nation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſouls periſh, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4 6. and go down to hell every hour in the year, one where or other: yea if it be againſt the Errors of the times, which are up and down in every Corner, as certainly it is, becauſe ſo contrary to Antichriſts doctrine whoſe Biſhope, Prieſts and Clergy could never endure to hear it without ſpitting at it, knowing they muſt all down, yea their gain as <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſaid; if Chriſt and his Kingdom once get up, as undoubtedly it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pace.</p>
            <p>Further you this Work which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o full of glory; and the leading Card to Romes deſtruction, the worlds converſion Jews, Turks, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>agans, much more our neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>France, Spain</hi> and others: yea this Nation may be as the riſing of the Sun to the world, the Son of rigteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49710:14"/> 
               <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 1. who muſt ariſe in every place and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit all Nations, let us give him firſt ours, and from hence let him ſhine gloriouſly in the gifts and graces of his Spirit, yea make the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and an Univerſity for the Saints, and every Publick place, a place to take degrees; pray they can already, and Preach they would as well might they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe one as well as the other.</p>
            <p>Let the Fountains run freely, and from theſe living ones let the in-dwellings of God flow forth, to water dry, yea to water empty places, which you judge not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable for the preſent, till Univerſities be recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yea filled with the holy Ghoſt, and learning, but one of twenty takes not right this way: can two univerſities fill the world at that rate: thouſands are too little for our own Land, what can now and then one doe to ſupply eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry barren place, and a great one ſpoil many, yea to preach to every Creature: Amongſt which, if but one periſh through your withholding labourers that would freely work in the Lords Vineyard, you are guilty, but if milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons periſh, how, and what then? Blood will be required here here, and the Lord convince you.</p>
            <p>We are not againſt you all this while: nor will we ever be: Give us what we do deſire for the good of all men: yea give us that, and we will be your ſervants upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, be ye ſick, be ye abſent, be ye where you will, we will preach for you, never whilſt we live againſt you in any kind whatſoever.</p>
            <p>For the Lords ſake truſt and try us once or twice, we have the faith of Chriſtians, and that we pawn again, give us but your help, and a little countenance; and you ſhall have all we have, heart, hand and purſe. And now we pray again:</p>
            <p>Good Miniſters, good Fathers, for the Lords ſake do not ſlight gifts and graces, and the Breathing of the Spirit, nor break our hearts with long delay, we long to be omnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, magnifying Chriſt, yea to be pouring out his blood to the world, yea we would turn him inſide out,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49710:14"/> yea we would make the moſt of Chriſt, and all of Chriſt, all his works in us, and all his works without us; all his gifts all his graces, all his Ordinances, as far as we may, we would fain be handling, ye the love of Chriſt, and the lovelineſſe of Chriſt, the ſweetneſſe of his Perſon, the joyes of his Spirit, and greatneſſe of his Merit, for the worſt of ſinners, that we would be talling, yea and our own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences, what of him we know, what of him we ſee, feel and enjoy here, beſides what we hope for (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 9.) another day when he and we his Members ſhall meet and appear altogether to give the world one confounding ſhew, we ſhall never appear till then, but then we ſhall: beloved, now are we the Sonnes of God, but it doth not yet appear what we ſha be, but <hi>when Chriſt who is our life ſhal appear we ſhall appear (Col.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>John</hi> 3. 2.) <hi>with him in glory;</hi> would we might beg leave to tell the world this, and warn them as <hi>Noah</hi> did, we would then ſave them as <hi>Lot</hi> was, yea we would ſmite men and ſave men, like <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Zacheus,</hi> ſtrip men and cloath them by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, yea, we would perſwade men from the wayes of ſin, by telling them the terrour of the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 11. yea, we would fetch men, the worſt of men from the high waies and hedges, and compell them into Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 23. Yea, dead ones from the grave of ſin, and make them live again, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. Yea, and as we would raiſe them up, ſo we would fetch them down from the pinnacle, and top of all earthly glories, to glory in a crucified Chriſt, like <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 6. 14.</p>
            <p>All this we would do, and all this we could do by the grace of God, if the Miniſters would but let, (the godly Miniſters) for the Lords ſake ſtand a little by; yea, ſtand away ſtraight, or elſe we will preach you down, and pray you down, write you down and pull you down headlong by faith and Gods aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Men, Brethren and Fathers, hear ye this day what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches, and harden not your hearts <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 8. Yea, if you have an ear, hear what
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49710:15"/> Chriſt ſaith to the Churches; yea, to you, and your Churches, which are neither hot not cold, but let us come amongſt them or elſe he and we will ſpew you all out toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Rev. 3. 15, 16. Some cry out, let us do it ſtraight, we have ſcarce patience for a day, but the Spirit waiteth long, grieve not, yea, quench not the Spirit, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 19, 20. Mark that Scripture.</p>
            <p>Oh ye Miniſters of <hi>England, London, White-Hall</hi> and thereabouts, but will none hear and ſee who is with us like the little Cloud with <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18. 44. Our chariots are as ſtrong as yours, yea, more and more numberleſſe, look if ye can by Faith, you may ſee the day for us, and the many thouſands with us.</p>
            <p>Cannot you ſee Scripture and Propheſies juſt a fulfilling? Is the world blinde? hear ye the ſtriking of the clocks if you be indeed awaked, and aware of the dayes coming on, the Lords Day, yea, the Spirits day, wherein he will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt every thing that oppoſeth, yea, he will be a fire, and burn up all, hay, ſtubble, and the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 11, 12. Your ſitting and your ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, if it be not for him, as well as from him, yea if you be againſt the Spirits coming forth, this winde ſhall blow you hither and thither, like the chaff; yea, your very name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the earth and preſence of his people.</p>
            <p>Watchmen, watchmen, are you all aſleep? Hear the Travellers of Sion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. 5. call, and ask you what it is a clock, yea, they tell you what it is, and how the night is far ſpent, and the day juſt at hand; Yea, the Lords day, a day of reſt to his people, but diſquiet to the inhabitants of the earth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. 30. Yea, to them who are at eaſe in Sion, <hi>(Amos</hi> 6. 1, 7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 9) and never minde her travails.</p>
            <p>Take heed ye Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets, improperly ſo called, yea, and all ye Rulers of the earth, eſpecially ye whom we are treating with for our liberty, which we charge you to preach up, for 'tis the year of Jubile that is come, <hi>Lev.</hi> 25. 10. Sions captives ſome <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 126. 1.) of them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49710:15"/> we are, yea, we warn you by the Trumpet of the Lord ſo to do: <hi>Noah</hi> being warned of God, prepared an Ark, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. do you do the like, yea, prepare an Ark of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from my Lord Protector for us, and your ſelves eſpecially, we fear not, the Lord and his Word will ſave us, yea, his Arm ſhall ſave us, for we are children that will not lie, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 8. nor do not lye, for it is the truth we ſtand for, nor can ye do any thing againſt it if ye would. This Rock will break and daſh yee all in pieces, ſet you up who will; yea, this truth hinted, will prick you to the heart, if ye kick againſt them that maintain it.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould ye that are for God, and have been ſo all your daies many of you, fight now againſt him; take heed, and take that Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 39. Yea, again take heed leſt ye be found ſo doing through pride, ſelf-haſtineſſe, or any thing.</p>
            <p>Men, Brethren, and Preachers, we babes and children warn you old men and Fathers, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 12. Yea, we write theſe things unto you Fathers, becauſe ye have known him and owned him all your daies, that was from the beginning; yea, we know ye know him, and this to be his minde, yea, a Truth according to his minde, that we now ſtand and plead thus for, your conſcience tells you it is ſo, we know it doth ſo, and before the Lord, we think moſt of your conſciences know it, but ſomething or another troubles, fear of errors, fear of ſlighting, meanes and maintainance, honour and eſteem from men, which if you be pleaſers of, you know what is ſaid, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 44. But fear ye none of all theſe things, do not perplex your hearts this way, fear him whom ye ſhould fear, our King and yours, the King of Saints, great and marvellous are thy works Lord God Almightie, Juſt and true are thy wayes O King of Saints, who ſhall not fear thee O Lord, and glorifie thy Name; all nations ſhall come and worſhip before thee, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. 4. A ſweet Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but to the point, fear not Errours, which we think is one of your great and main feares, fear not that, God is wiſer than man, ye than the wiſeſt of the ſons of men; we
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49710:16"/> nor you never play the fools more than when we ſet our wiſdomes to his; minde what we ſay; Ye may think to ſave the truth of Chriſt as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> did the Ark, by putting out your counſel, take <hi>Gamaliells</hi> counſel, we have done: ye, that of the Ark which erring ye turn againſt us: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> was forbid to touch the Ark, we are bid to build up one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and covet the beſt gifts, yea, to Propheſie, 1 Cor. 14. 1. <hi>Iude</hi> 20. which we do, <hi>men of old ordained unto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation creep forth with us, Iude</hi> 4. not without the minde of God, <hi>and broach damnable Errours, yea, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord that bought them;</hi> In zeal, as you think, for him to ſave his truths, Word, and Ordinances, it may be your ſelves, yea, all from falling, ye put your hand, power, policy and humane wiſdome againſt theſe men and us with them, in true zeal as you think to ſave theſe truths, well, if ye do, we think what we know, and we know what we think, and tell you too of the Texts.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 33, 39.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49710:16"/>
            <head>A Word to the well ſatisfied, ſanctified, and Godly of the Nation, who are in Chriſt Jeſus Saints by Calling. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2.</head>
            <p>ANd for you of all formes and Judgements that are good and ſound, we have a word to each; and firſt for you Churches, and holy Brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 1. We ſhall need to ſay but little to you about our Modell or Petition; Yea, nothing at all, but ſtraight chooſe ye out from amongſt your ſelves men that are full of the holie Ghoſt like <hi>Stephen, Acts</hi> 6. 3. zealous as <hi>Paul,</hi> ſelf-denying as <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, who alwaies pointed to Chriſt denying himſelf, that like to the other <hi>John</hi> may preach nothing but love, love to God and all his wayes, love to Saints in all their formes, ſuch men there are, ſuch men chooſe from amongſt your ſelves; yea, and be ſure they be ſo, to promote this work in the publick places.</p>
            <p>But firſt call a meeting, ye that are in fellowſhip, have many pray ſpend one or two in a ſerious conſultation in and about this Modell for your next Petition, I mean not for words but ſubſtance; ye that I pray conſult, the minde of God is amongſt, the light of God in, and the truth of God profeſſed by you; lay the golden Rule, the Reed of the Temple, the Word or the Modell and Petition to this Rule, trie, ſee, ſearch, and find if it be not ſo: But herein you are ſatisfied already; Yea, I think, ſcarce a man otherwiſe; What then? Up, and be doing, for the Lord is with, and hath laid this as a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49710:17"/> preſent work before you; Yea, do not you ſee it on your Tables as you ſit, and in your Bibles too; Yea, is it not, and was it not in your hearts long ago; well, you had never ſuch a nick of time as now to promote ſo good a work: One man can do more than fifty could former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you know who we mean, you have the ear of God; Yea, you his little Church and Churches have ſo, and the heart of this man too: Pray what ſhould hinder? It is but ask and have; two humble lines from one of your Society doth this work, we will warrand you, but for company ſake which is good, yea, exceeding good in a good matter; You may all draw a line or two of love and liking to the Work, and when he that hath our hearts, as well as we his, ſhall be humbly preſented with theſe deſires, we ſhall then ſee what a gracious anſwer we ſhall ſoon find believe it; the Lord our God, nor the Lord protector our true old Friend, and good Friend under him, can denie nothing to the Saints, and little Churches, ſcarce himſelf, eſpecially ſuch a thing as this as tends ſo much to the good of all ſouls; peace and welfare of the Church and State, the glorie of both, which is moſt under his care now: ſo then it is but to ſeek and find, ask and have; one knock by a Petition, and this door of Liberty flies wide open, beating down all that ſtand againſt it.</p>
            <p>Well, is the Work before you, yea, on your Tables, in your hearts; Yea, and put into your hand by God, and his poor ſinning ſervants; do not delay time, it requires haſte, poſt-haſte, therefore do not delay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye know not what they are, nor where they are, nor of whoſe judgement, all which concernes juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; The work is the Lords, and before you by his Providence, ſo we ſay again, do not ye be buſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> once complained none was like him; Why ſo? Every one minded his own things, and none the things of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 21. but God forbid his Churches ſhould do ſo, or ſay what Liberty ſhall we have, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49710:17"/> we have to exerciſe our gifts that is ſelfiſh, why ſhould one or the other ſay ſo, may not all have leave, one as well as another, ſure none will preach what the people cannot bear, nor any thing diſputeful, or to bring in Members to their own Churches, but to the univerſal, one Church, of which wholly and ſolelie Chriſt is the King, Paſt our, Prieſt and Prophet; yea, we ſay, none will ſpeak or Preach otherwiſe, that would ſtraight confound us all, and ſpoil all our meetings then indeed; but we are not jealous of you in the leaſt, though we thus ſpeak, for we know you have learned to do all things in decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 40. not any thing in confuſion; Yea, you have the minde of Chriſt dwelling in you, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 16. and will do nothing in ſtrife and vain-glory <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 3. boaſting in fleſh, <hi>Gal</hi> 5. 26. wrangling or jangling, but in love and meekneſſe, with a ſweet Spirit of humilitie to all good Magiſtrates and Miniſters, which he hath ſet over us, for our good, that we may live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, Godly and honeſtly in both our Callings.</p>
            <p>Now Brethren fare ye well, fare ye well again, peace and the God of peace which paſſeth all underſtanding now and ever knit and keep <hi>(Phil.</hi> 4. 7.) all your Churches, members, hearts and mindes in the knowledge of God our Father, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our deareſt dear, and beloved one, theſe things, perſons, and this Work be now and ever in your hearts, and the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all, Amen, Amen, Amen. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49710:18"/>
            <head>A Word to our other Brethren; yea, to all you that love our Lord Jeſus, the God and Father of him that raiſed him from the dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 10.</head>
            <p>ANd to you that are travelling <hi>Sion-</hi>ward, ſome under one diſpenſation, ſome under another, even as the Lord pleaſeth, and perſwades the heart, which light of his in you, you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dare nor can go againſt, but on, on, as the Lord perſwades, from one degree unto another, until at laſt you come to ſee he himſelf, which you never do, nor can do fully in this vail of teares, though ſome draw nearer far than others, by meeting with more fountains, <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 84. 8.) loves and diſcoveries; Yet the God of gods, and fountain of all joyes and glories they never fully ſee, but in time may; Yea, undoubtedlie ſhall, <hi>And they ſhall ſee his face, Rev.</hi> 22. 4. and what I ſay to one I ſay to all, his face in whoſe <hi>preſence is fulneſſe of joy, at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore, Pſal.</hi> 16. 11. You which are travelling <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n-</hi>ward ſhall, ſome it may be with your Cimbals and inſtruments of joy, <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping as the Roe upon the mountains of ſpices, Cant.</hi> 8. 14. through the indwellings of God, the high diſcoveries and joyes of his Spirit, which the joye of the Harveſt is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver like in ſubſtance or operation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 3.</p>
            <p>Well, ſome are travelling ſo, with theſe joyes and glories in their heart and eye, others ſilently and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eetlie, yea, greatly mourning and lamenting for the abſence of him, who ſhould be nigh them and in them, Chriſt their Bridegroom and husband; <hi>Luk.</hi> 5. 35. and the comforts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49710:18"/> of Chriſt his Spirit and joyes, all which they want through the indwellings of ſin, temptations and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions for ſin, to all theſe we have a word, a ſweet word, and this it is:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They ſhall all return like the rivers in the South from their captivity, Pſal</hi> 126. 4. of ſin, bondage and temptations to ſin with joy, <hi>yea, they ſhall bring their ſheaves with them, Pſal.</hi> 126. 6.</p>
            <p>The fruits of this penitential, holy and heavenlie ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which be it, where it will, and as much as it will, it is never to be repented of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10. For on the heads of all hearts where this ſorrow now dwels ſhall be <hi>everlaſting joy, Iſa.</hi> 61. 7. yea, Crownes of Roſes, joyes and glories, theſe ſorowes now are pleiting, and when the work is done, like a mighty Eagle, <hi>ſorrow and ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall fly away, and all teares ſhall be wiped clean away from theſe blubbered cheeks;</hi> God himſelf ſhall do it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 4.</p>
            <p>Wherefore comfort ye your ſelves and one another with theſe words, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in another caſe, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 18. In the mean time here is a work commended to your hands from your brethren, your fellow members, Citizens and travellers, yea, the ſame way with you, whom you and every one of you are bound by God, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all the neareſt relations and obligations under heaven to do for all that you can, and for the preſent your hearts and hands are deſired to this good Work, for your good God and our Lord Jeſus the glorie of both, and your own and our liberty; Yea, your own, for amongſt you are many <hi>more precious than choice ſilver, Lam</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. 12. Yea, the Starres of heaven mark well what we ſay, and their graces would <hi>ſhine like the gold of Ophir, (Iſa.</hi> 45. 9.) where they called to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent work: which with tears, we beſeech you Brethren in Chriſts ſtead, and for Chriſts ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. to ſet about in good earneſt, and for the preſent get a meeting two or three amongſt your ſelves, God
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49710:19"/> ſhall pay the Meſſengers that bring them together, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
            <p>What if you ſend a Summons ten or twentie miles round to meet in ſome convenient places; Yea, Tickets, one man and one Saint unto another, 'tis the work of God, and the generation; Yea; a Work that will wagg before you ſet your hand, if our great Counſel do but hear an inkling, they know your labour of love, and the godlie will help; Yea, he that ſits at the helm will do it himſelf, 'tis in his heart, yea, and thoughts ſo to do; yea, to put you on it, and wonders why ye ſtay ſo long in the Work of God, knowing he hath power now to do any thing for you: you in the Armie have nothing elſe to do, and can pray and preach well, if you have not forgot that and the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph, Amos</hi> 6. 6. which is ſorer than all that you have freed us from: Yea, than the <hi>Egyptian</hi> one, we value not to make brick, maintain you or any thing; Yea, your wives and coaches to ſet but your helping hand; yea, the Lord ſet that, we need not your ſword but your faith, praiers and Petition; Yea, one word from the Counſel of Officers at St. <hi>Jameſes</hi> doth it, and if one among you all ſcruple, ask Mr. <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dack,</hi> he is right for the work, we are ſure, old <hi>Hugh</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and moſt of your Independent Miniſters, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel Caryll,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sterrey,</hi> Doctor <hi>Owen,</hi> the man preaches well and clear; theſe will all help, however good Captains, good Souldiers, Serjeants, Saints, and Chriſtians, ſpeak one to another of the thing, for the Lord Jeſus ſake, 'tis right in your eyes, yea, your own practiſe, and we have learned of you, and will ſet it up by the grace of God, if you lay it by to look for Arrears and Debenters, which when this is done you may: Yea, marry, buy and ſell too: ſo ye do not forget the Rock, and living unto him who like a River followed you in the Van and Rear, three wilderneſſes together, ſome once or twice over, and ſmote the rock again and again, yea, your enemies in every place where you or they met, <hi>Oh</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49710:19"/> 
               <hi>that men would praiſe the Lord,</hi> may the Armie now ſay, <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever,</hi> yea, ſing this 136. Pſalm, as long as you live, yea, breath; and yet we dedicate it to you once again; yea, to every one of your hearts, 'tis ſo pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and full to your condition; And pray when you ſound your brave triumphing ſounds, Remember us the laſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and how much of your love and zeal in this particular you have loſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>And now we come again to you Men and Brethren, which we were treating with before; we medled with the ſword or godly of the Army about the ſame thing ſtill, if you have not diſpatched your Summons to all men aind places where the fear of the Lord dwels, rich, poor, hgh, low, young and old, blinde, halt, and lame; yea, get them altogether, to conſult, do not ſtay, and ſay one to another, Pray ye Sir do you, and Pray ye Sir do you; ſend for old Father <hi>Eli,</hi> and you for young <hi>Samuell,</hi> and you for <hi>Zacheus,</hi> we, Chriſt and his people will all dine there, <hi>Luk,</hi> 19. 5. and treat afterwards about reſtoring every man his own at leaſt, eſpecially the Liberty of the Saints, and promulgation of the Goſpel: but let every one; yea, ſome in particular, go to all as the Meſſengers of the Churches 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 23. and let them charge them in the Name of God to come ſtraight away by the morning light, the light of God in them; yea, charge them by this day, and charge them by this night of Gods withdrawing from them, they delay no time, if they be about a buſineſſe of their own, dealing in their Calling, let them ſhut up, and bring them ſtraight away, if they be about the buſineſs of another, or medling with the State, bring them ſtraight away, if they be about their holy Worſhip and Chriſtian duties, bring them ſtraight away, yea, from the Lords Table to meet the Lords people; Men may leave the beſt of duties upon ſome occaſions, in a caſe of neceſſity, and ſuch a one is this; yea, the ſeaſon of the year requires it, look elſe ſaith Chriſt to every Saint in <hi>England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> do not you ſee the eares white: <hi>Pray ye therefore the Lord of the harveſt to thruſt forth labourers into his harvest, John</hi> 4. 35.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49710:20"/> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 9 38 Yea, pray my Lord Protector ſo to do, or elſe pray him, <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> will never ſend enough. What do we gazing ſo after theſe, as once the Angel ſaid, <hi>Oh ye men of Galilee, Acts</hi> 1. 11. So ſay we, Ye men of the Army, City, Town and Countrey, why do ye all ſo gaze and gape after thoſe men that were taken away once; ſo ſhall they come again, yea, the very men ſhall come again, though ſome without their gownes, yet their Univerſity gifts ſhall not be wanting, the graces of the Spirit, the Gifts of Gods People, Oh my friends, many of theſe you gape and gaze after are gone, and gone in the late warres, I hope juſt the ſame men are not come again to another, much leſſe to the ſame place. This we never fought for, or looked for, unleſſe they were taken by their ſequeſtrations up into heaven, I mean godly ſorrow and Repentance for their former ſins, popery, pride, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of bread, ignorance, emptineſſe, drunkenneſſe and thirſt, yea for our blood, which is precious in the fight of the Lord, ſo ſaith <hi>David, Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of all his Saints, Pſal.</hi> 116. 15.</p>
            <p>Well, but ſhall we truſt theſe thirſty wretches with our ſouls once again, rather then a known godly Chriſtian of ten or twenty years, ſtanding gifts and abilities.</p>
            <p>Good and godly Tryers do not you do ſo wickedly, and <hi>ſin againſt God, Gen</hi> 19 7. <hi>There be of the Synagogue of Satan, which ſay they are Jewes, Rev.</hi> 2. 9. Yea, they will ſay ſo now, becauſe ye are uppermoſt, but try them well, and you ſhall find them lyars; they guilt themſelves it may be by praying for the State, and the Lord Protector can they by the Spirit do ſo, or Preach.</p>
            <p>Well, we hope ye will not take tinne, and lay by ſilver, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 22. for all the keyes of <hi>David</hi> in your hand, power to open and ſhut, whom and when you pleaſe, which ſhould be wholly in the hands of Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. 22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 7. Two ſweet Texts in the eyes and hearts of Saints. But to our other friends once again, whom we muſt intreat they are ſo backward, ſome through the worlds pleaſures,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49710:20"/> profits, places cannot give a meeting, no, it may be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ry week, though it were to be wiſhed they could, not becauſe they, the Saints more imployed and richer, have better gifts the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poor, but for their own ſouls and graces ſake, for a good meeting is better for the good of their ſouls, and ſtrength of their graces, than a good bargain or dinner, either much more then a little idleneſſe, ſome walk abroad, others ride ſome viſite <hi>Joan</hi> hold my ſtaffe t'other day, but theſe rich Saints cannot come to our poor weekly meetings, I wiſh they may to this good work, 'its their good Maſters who hath bleſt them thus.</p>
            <p>Oh but others which have more peace, joy, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion far then theſe, them I hope will come; but ſome are ſo full of cares, feares and poverties that they cannot give a meeting, unleſſe it be the Lords day about five of the clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, Well, once a week would do no hurt, nor bring the world backward, rather thee forward and upward, and it is beſt thriving ſo, having food and rayment, let us be content ſaid a good man, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 8 for our ſelves and children it is implyed; paſſions may come ſoon enough and may be God himſelf will be one, and that is enough ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119. 57.</p>
            <p>In the mean time come you to the Generall Aſſembly of all Saints and Church of the firſt born, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 23. Yea, to the firſt in the Work of the Lord, which will be good ſo to do at laſt, it is beſt at firſt, and moſt honourable, God ever mindes the firſt fruits, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 19. and claims the firſt Male.</p>
            <p>Chriſt the firſt Goſpel Miniſter ſets up him above <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 11. one Preached Repentance, the other Pardon. Minde it Presbyterians, too many of you ſet up <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and ſet the other by. Yea, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt both down; You know how I mean, one for an Antinomian, and the other for a Flyer; Yea, ſometimes a Lyer, to make up the number of the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, becauſe you for the preſent, it may be do not ſee them, yet trulie for my part, I do love exceedingly to ſee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49710:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49710:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49710:22"/> a Preacher as well as hear him, yet I muſt confeſſe they flye ſometimes higer than I can well tell yet, or ſee where they are, or hear either what they ſay underſtandingly, which I do not well like, not dare not too haſtily judge. I know but in part; Yea, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> we all know but in part, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 9.</p>
            <p>But when I do conſider Chriſt and the Apoſtles, moſt of which ſlew very low; Yea, preached according to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and beſt advantage for the people, that is a good rule, but to flye to high is dangerous, and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, one may get a fall, and the other two be dazled, Yea, ſtagger in his judgement, and miſled it may be in judgement from the Lord, for want of love to plain truths, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 20. 11, 12. and too much too high Diſputes, the fruit of ſpirituall pride, ſo I like not men too high, but as heavenly as they will, in Emblems, Divine things, and Meditations: Yea, I ſay, I love to hear men ſo Preach, and they take us up like <hi>John</hi> in the Spirit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 10. or <hi>Paul</hi> in his rapture, but theſe are ſtill in <hi>New-England, Old-England</hi> hath but few, ſo many changes have been of late, and every change diſtempers, ſome Miniſters halfe a year at leaſt, after Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> head; how long before the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians ſettled right to the work of Preaching Chriſt up, down ſelf; Yea, are they yet at it, eſpecially the latter, I do not know, but I have heard a little; But will you hear a fool and Friend gladly by way of advice, <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>David</hi> did ſo, of you know whom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will you lift up Chriſt more in Prayer; Yea, your ſelves and the Saints in what God hath done for us in a way of praiſes, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 34. 56. as well as what we are by nature, and that is bad enough in our ſelves, yet in Chriſts righteouſneſſe we are ſtill righteous; Minde that, however confeſſe no more then you are guilty, and in that confeſſion diſtinguiſh between men and men, and this hint to in your preaching, and I ſhall preſume no more, Lift him up there who is the true brazen Serpent, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 14, 15. for every eye to look on; Spread upon the pole of the Croſſe, with his Crown of thornes faſt nailed to the Law,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49710:22"/> yea, juſtice of God for ſatisfaction, and ſo let his ſide run freely, yea, tell the world of his Speech. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man, behold thy ſon, Iohn</hi> 19. 26. Yea, ſinner, ſinner thy Saviour, for it is thee he calls as well as ſhe, and when ye have clearlie ſo done by right diſtinguiſhing between the Law and Goſpel, what he hath freely done for us; Yea, to the uttermoſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and what he requires of us more then he hath given or promiſed to us; and ſo ye give us the very man that once looked down from <hi>Mount Olives, Luk</hi> 19. 41. with ſoul-longings for us: Yea, ye give us then the very names of Chriſt Jeſus, the Lamb of God, that takes away the ſins of of the world, <hi>(Iohn</hi> 1. 29.) before Repentance, and from thence gives right repentance never to be repented of, world without end, Amen,</p>
            <p>Will ye try a little this Doctrine, and give us this wine reſerved for the latter age, <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 2. at leaſt one cup full now and then, and you will draw the hearts of all men more then you do unto Chriſt, and your ſelves, and off from all ſin and ſorrow, yea, our lives will be better, and our ſtirrings quicker when you pour this oyl of gladeneſſe upon our heads and hearts. And now you that have it come away, to the old work and Petition for our Liberty to preach the <hi>Scapegoat, Lev.</hi> 16 21. the <hi>Paſchall Lamb, Exod.</hi> 12. 21. <hi>the brazen Serpent,</hi> but ſome a little ſcruple at this, namely our Call; if it be but ſo, a little ſcruple, come away, never be too nice in a good Work, for an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart, 'tis for thouſands, indeed it is ſo.</p>
            <p>Oh but it is diveliſh, and damnable ſaith many of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, honeſt ſincere and godly ones, ſay and think ſo happily becauſe they have been taught ſo that they have been the truth of it is too much, but for theſe that thought ſo, and was once of that judgement, will you ſtill maintain it therefore, I hope not ſo; again many ſee, and will not ſee, but are ſinfully ſilent, marry pray God ſome great Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be not ſo (well, when one comes t'other will, the people, yea, both in time, how many of the latter would
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49710:23"/> not come to a meeting till they found the ſweetneſſe, but then like ſome cattell having taſted ſweet corn; how did they run and cry, come husband, come wife, let us go to ſuch and ſuch a place to day, there is a very ſweet meeting ten or twenty of them in a Parlour, they begin and end with Prayer, two or three ſpeak, but one at a time, all to one point, I am ſure by the ſame Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13. it was ſo ſweet, and did warm my very heart and ſoul, ſaith one that hath tryed; Well, will ye try now, you that are againſt the publick exerciſings of the People; Oh but I am not for that yet; Why? A private life is good, but a publick Saint is beſt, if a Private meeting of ten or twenty Believers, and others be ſo ſweet, the latter ſaying no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor the former but about forgiveneſſe, faith, and Repentance, how God pardoned them, and how ſweet it was, what now they will do, and how much through grace love again this God, and that the Lord is gracious in himſelf, in his Son and Promiſes, he is good to all, yea, all his works ſaith one; yea, to Saints and the worſt of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; Yea, ſaith a third, or elſe I had been in hell; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you ſaith a fourth Saint to the Sinners then; Yea, you may believe now, look unto him and be ſaved, ſtraight from that Text, <hi>Look unto me all the ends of the earth, and be ſaved, Iſa.</hi> 45. 22.</p>
            <p>Leave and loath your ſins after this, home runnes the ſinner and cryes God was amongſt them, makes reſtitution ſtraight crying out with <hi>David, Away from me all ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquity, Pſal.</hi> 6. 8. which another hearing of cryes, this was good if it were ſo, alwayes when they meet to Preach, but they wrangle much, fall out and judge one another very ſeldome we aſſure you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſet meetings, carried on by a knot of true lovers, ſober able Chriſtians, but from whence comes the Errours ſome cry, we have none amongſt us, we anſwer for our ſelves in two or three meetings that we know, but do hold the ſame truths, with our Miniſters in every particular; Yea, we are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into one and the ſame faith with them, by the ſame
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49710:23"/> Spirit through the ſame blood, 1 Cor. 12. 13. Yea, we differ in nothing in the world, but that we would be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up and converting ſinners too, thinking it is our duty, <hi>When thou art converted ſtrengthen thy brother, Luk.</hi> 22. 32.</p>
            <p>Oh, but from whence then comes your Errours? Moſt from Miniſters ſcandalous, not knowing the truth, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times through falſhood and the Miniſters fancy, they ſay ſuch a thing, and ſuch a thing is abroad, and ſpread them in their Pulpits Errours which the people who are ever heavy in hearing to good and ſound truth, often catch the badd, 'tis good in ſome caſes to ſee and not to ſee, we think it is in this, eſpecially not to ſay we ſee what we hear from three or four hands, every one adding or diminiſhing; through weakneſſe or wickedneſſe, but the Errours and erroneous are none of us, nor of the ſettled meeting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, whoſe liberty we plead for, but rather ſome giddy headed gadding Chriſtians, that runs up and down, peeps in here, and peeps in there, no where out of love, but in every place to object and wrangle, and make a little way for an old Errour, or a whimſie according to the rule of <hi>Paul, Firſt in love we check him once or twice, Tit.</hi> 3. 10. if they be not too groſſe, however they are gone, or elſe ever ſilent, and converted from their ſin; Yea, many times we gain ſome that are juſt a going by underpropping them, when they lean a little from the truth, by neglecting good Miniſters, hearing bad; Our meetings to hear bad Diſputes, who, nor where we neither own nor know, nor love theſe things, yea, we love nothing but what may tend to the edification of one or another, nor will do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in your publick place when we come about a moneth hence, ſome I hope will provide room or matter for us, but you ſhall never come while you breath, ſaith a Formaliſt, one that hath every thing of a Saint, but the reall life, power, gifts, joyes and graces, and theſe men will envy this light, life and power, leaſt other men ſhould expect as much from them, becauſe they have paſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49710:24"/> all along under the ſame names and notions of good and godly men, and ſo we ſhall be ſlighted, ſay they, and in time looſe our eſteem for our godlineſſe, though we have followed them in their very ſteps, truly they that ſeem to have ſomething, and are nothing, will in time looſe that, that is certain, <hi>To him that hath ſhall be given, and from him that hath not ſhall be taken away, even that which be ſeemeth to have, Mat.</hi> 13. 12.</p>
            <p>But be this far from a good heart ſo to think, be his gifts or graces as ſmall as they will; have not the members of the Church their peculiar gifts? Are all the Lords people Prophets, or have all the gifts of light knowledge, grace and power alike? No, but every one hath as God hath given, nor is it requiſite it ſhould be ſo; <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes of babes, young men and old, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>Every Member need not be an eye, nor every Saint a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, yet every one is to covet the beſt gift, eſpecially this of Propheſying, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 31. or expounding Scripture, but he that cannot may be as much humble, yea, as much uſefull in another way, therefore let not honeſt men and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble walking Chriſtians fear the loſſe of this eſteem, but ſubſcribe to the Modell, Legall men and Phariſees and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites will be offended more than any, if every man preach thus: It was ſo in Chriſts time, and after, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 2. but we ſtand not for every man, but for ſome able men judged to be ſo, by ſome that are able ſo to do, What if godly Chriſtians ſhould upon a ſummons from among themſelves, or from a Magiſtrate, chooſe two, three, or four, as the place can afford to be as publick ſpeakers, as your Burgeſſes are choſen one, two or three for ſuch a Town, and two or three for ſuch a Pariſh, not too many at the firſt by no meanes; better one old ſpeaker then three or four young ones coming on for the preſent, will ye take a fools advice, 'tis but a hint, not a platform, or a rule for all; that were high preſumption; Yea, to make ones ſelf St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but let me ſay what we think would do well, leave your young ſpeakers coming on to the private, we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49710:24"/> can bear with one anothers weakneſſe there, and gain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> much by one as t'other many times, but ſtill for the preſent able to divide the word, batter down ſin, yea, the ſinners, and raiſe up the Saints, eſpecially the mourners of <hi>Sion, Iſa.</hi> 40. 1. anſwer all objections bravely, preach bold and humbly, put out theſe firſt, and the other forward as much as may be, and hereto we, who cannot well tell what to ſay in this nice point, would not be too ſtrait laced in giving leave to any to ſpeak or object a little, deſiring every mans Light may be held forth, moſt where his life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is known to be good and godly; yet we think they may do as Parſons do ſpeak, one for another that are well known; And what if it were by a kind of Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we mean the approbation of the Saints thereabouts; yea, and it would be very good to have as much love, leave, and liking as may be from others, and we hear of many that are free and willing to hear us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> before or after Sermon, every day we hope to gain more and more, yea we have gained much already this way.</p>
            <p>And this we add further, You that chuſe theſe men, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your Intereſt with your Miniſter of the Pariſh, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to know who it is, what it is, when it is, and why it is he ſhould ſpeak in the Publick this requeſt of yours, his love or liking of the man or mens Spirits, may put him, himſelf upon the breaking of the ice, and recommending of the work to the people once or twice, then the thing is done, laughing, jeering, ſtanding up, the Newes, and talking of it, and all kind of hubbubbs are huſht and gone for ever, and we have our Liberty without the loſſe or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of an hair to any man living.</p>
            <p>Miniſters, our hearts, hands, purſes, we feaſt them, they ſometimes us; yea, and we will better all their meanes, be it Tythes, be it what it will be; yea, we will look to their charge in caſe of death, own them, and do for them as our own Brethren; yea, and a thouſand times more, in requitall of their love to us, and the truth, which then they have to purpoſe manifeſted to the world round about; yea,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49710:25"/> and then every eye ſhall ſee that they are not in the leaſt, what too many are to prone to think, yea, and haſtily to judge.</p>
            <p>But yet a word more to our ſetters up, in caſe ſuch a one or more, ſhould through weakneſſe, and the divell which will not be wanting every way to tempt and try, fall into any ſcandalous ſin, one or more, yea, or in caſe he do not, but grow proud and ſelfiſh, which that there may be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of, we admoniſh or elſe give our thoughts may be from the minde of the Lord in this thing alſo: That then our Chriſtian friends and neighbours, the Godly of the Pariſh, yea, one or two of theſe bodies may for the honour of Chriſt, the Vindication of the Goſpel; yea, and for the good and humbling of the guifted Chriſtian brother, with a great great deal of humility, grave and godly exhortation call in, and take back his Commiſſion, with a dehortation to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any more for the preſent, yet after a full manifeſtation of his godly ſorrow, not for a week, moneth, ſcarce three or four let it be returned, and when ever it is, with a great deal of grave exhortation, yea, and prayer among your ſelves; yea, ordain none nor Ticket none without that, nor let never none claim to, or look upon himſelf as an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Miniſter, but as a kind of aſſiſtant, much leſſe to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with many things quite out of their ſphere, as baptizing, burying, miniſtring the Sacrament, or any ſuch kind of works, for theſe are without diſpute the proper office of the Miniſter who hath the charge of the place, and not of theſe who help onely of good will, exerciſing not every day ſo conſtantly as the Miniſter better miſſe three Lords dayes than not hit one, my meaning is not good and ſound matter; and now I think how they were ſerved that went to caſt out Divels, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 15, 16. upon whom the evill-Spirits fell, and cryed out againſt, wounding, tearing, and ſending them away naked and aſhamed, ſo ſay we; haply a Ranter vain or ungodly man may attempt to imitate or do, in vain glory, but let all ſuch take heed, the beadel, people, or Church-wardens do
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49710:25"/> not fall upon them; nothing will preſerve a man from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief but ſincerity in ſuch a caſe, therefore let all take heed what they attempt from the example of theſe vagabond Jews, and how they do diſturb any congregation, or come with teares, vain wanton notions or deluſions of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to diſturb our holy worſhip, and in caſe ſuch a man do come, mark the ſting or poyſon of the adder, and mildely give a hint of that, the Juſtice will take courſe if he come too often, but for once he may paſſe as he is, but no more by no meanes.</p>
            <p>But as I ſaid but now, Scribes Phariſees and Hypocrites will ſtorm and grieve exceedingly, notwithſtanding all theſe cautions, and cry down for pride, Schiſm, faction, new doctrine, and I know not what; yea, a legion of lyes they will raiſe againſt it, but this is one, yea, a thumper to, cry out ſo unleſſe it be in this ſence, they mean it hath been lying by a long time we do confeſſe, yea, and up by Antichriſt, but be it new or old it muſt be ſold and broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched every day, an old ſuit or faſhion long laid by, is a new when put on again, an old Antichriſtian Errour is the like, when it is new broached; but we are ſure this Goſpel-truth ſpurn'd at by the Miniſters whilſt they ſend a Poſt to <hi>Scotland</hi> for you know what, and what it coſt, is no new thing, but an old thing, and that muſt not be deſpiſed nor the old cuſtomes of the Saints in the Primitive times too.</p>
            <p>Take a bundle of Texts and weigh them at your leaſure, we are in haſte too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 4. 8. <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 28. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 11. <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 19, 20, 21. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 24, 25. <hi>Jud.</hi> 20. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 11. 14, 19, 20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 10, 11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 20. 21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>James</hi> 5. 19. 20. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Joel.</hi> 2. 28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 34. Col. 3. 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14, 15, 16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 16. 17. <hi>Num.</hi> 11. 26. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Surely ſome of theſe are to the purpoſe, and never a one in the Bibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lookes with a full and broad face againſt us: But to come to the old matter.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49710:26"/>
            <p> Well, are you for the work, or are you not? You bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the Miniſters, five to Mr. ſuch a one, and ten to Mr. ſuch a one, yea, and it may be twice as many to another, Oh ye captive daughters of <hi>Sion, Iſa</hi> 52. 2. Yea, <hi>Sinah,</hi> I had almoſt ſaid the children of the bond-woman, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 22, 25. But the Lord make you free, whoſe freemen you are, if you be Believers; have you never read that Text <hi>If the Son make you free, you are free indeed, John</hi> 8. 36. We know he hath, yea, we cry aloud, <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> all kinde of Antichriſtian bondage, and how faſt are you in, yea, tyed by the leg to one Pew or one Pulpit, daring ſcarce for your life, miſſe one Sermon in a whole year of one mans Preaching, when a hundred, may be five, are as good within a mile round, here in the City, but ſtill you ly groaning under ſuch a one, and ſuch a ones Cuſhion as it were, where he beates the Law, yea, breakes your heart, or at leaſt puzles and fills your ſoul with doubts; yea, almoſt quite off from believing that your ſins are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, which were pardoned long ago.</p>
            <p>For the Lords ſake do not ſigh, and cry, if I have not all grace, I have none, all faith, yea, to remove mountains, eſpecially that of Repentance, which they branch out four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty waies ſometimes, thirty of them in impoſſibilities, haſt thou a loathing of ſin, love and liking to Chriſt, Faith in and on Chriſt, to act and fetch comfort from Chriſt, it is enough; yea, haſt thou nothing of all this? Believe thy ſins pardoned, and they are pardoned; yea, believe it to be ſo really, and they are, as ſure as the Lord lives, fetch ſtrength from that, waſh thy face, dip thy head, back and belly in the blood of Chriſt, the Fountain ſet open for <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to waſh in, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14. 1. Yea, dabble day and night thy ſoul there, eſpecially in your hot dayes of temptations and accuſations; yea, in ſuch dayes lay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by your thoughts in the Fountain, dipping and diving of your ſouls like the little dive dapper, in the mean time <hi>put on thy, beautifull garments, Iſa.</hi> 42. 1. and come away, and do not cry, I am for <hi>Paul,</hi> and I am for <hi>Apolos,</hi> I am
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49710:26"/> for <hi>Cephas,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 22. I am for Chriſt, for ſo do many ſay, dividing him, but will you be for us, and our old work, you that ſay you are for Chriſt, we are in his way, and for his work, and reſolved upon it by the grace of God, you are for Chriſt in one, we for Chriſt in every man: Yea, to make him known to every man like <hi>Philip</hi> we would call <hi>Nathaniell, John</hi> 1. 45.</p>
            <p>Run and tell, yea, Preach, we was about to ſay with the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and with the Angel, ſhew where men have laid by Chriſt and Religion too in theſe times, yea, where and when again he is riſen in the ſouls of his, and with <hi>Stephen</hi> witneſſe theſe things almoſt with our blood, I do not ſee <hi>Stephen</hi> (now I think of it) had much more call then ſome whom we plead for, onely more of God, and zeal for God to encourage to the work, and I hope we ſhal have ſome to begin in every parriſh Church; if in caſe the Magiſtrate give not leave, this were a work of honour, and worthy to be chronicled amongſt the Miracles of the Saints, if ſuch a one ſhould a little ſuffer; yea, would we could but hear of one or two ſuffering in ſuch a kind of way what never a bold man in all the Churches now in <hi>London</hi> that dare come to ours. <hi>Margarets, Pauls, White-Hall, Covent-Garden</hi> or <hi>Clements,</hi> there you may be all well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and preach a little Sermon before the Miniſter comes in the Name of God, break the ice ſome body, make a gap in the hedg of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> we will widen it and follow in apace.</p>
            <p>Where is the Bell-weather of the Saints, I mean the brave; able, bold and gifted Chriſtian that can go on in his matter roundly, anſwer all objections bravely, look ſcoffers in the face boldly; yea, go on with his matter if in caſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtare, ſtand up on the top of the Pewes, whiſper one to another, never minding theſe things, yea, in caſe the Church Wardens, which are ſeldome good, cry, Pray Sir be quiet and make no diſturbance, Sir, we ſpeak for Chriſt and will till the Clerk or Miniſter come; if one ſheep go firſt, fourty ſtraight will follow; but by all means let us
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49710:27"/> firſt of all draw our Petition, if it be but three lines, yea, and let our hands be to it by all meanes, and not one man but every mans name be down, but not one more, than really godly and blameleſſe in their converſations, yea, let all ſuch in <hi>London,</hi> and all ſuch in <hi>England,</hi> yea, in <hi>Wales</hi> where they ſay they are good at the work already, and have very good ſucceſſe in one or two places, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple flock in amain, their Welch blood malignity and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out; yea, let all ſubſcribe; two, three or four parriſhes may, where the Saints be ſcarce, elſe every one a Petition by themſelves, yea, and as near as may be give notice one Church, one country to another ſo to do, yea, and come in Perſon as many as conveniently can, it will do my Lord Protector good to ſee ſome of his poor old friends and his Souldiers, Landlords once again, ſome of which he hath prayed with and for.</p>
            <p>What if a day, or two, three, or a week be loſt upon ſo good an accompt? My Lord will bear your charges down with his gracious anſwer; the great Councel hath prepared it already, if you will but come; Why do you ſtand ſtaying for a hand or two, when you have thouſands known to be good, godly, quiet, humble and ſelf-denying Chriſtians, ſome wil come the next day, but ſtay not you for any: We have ſtayed too long, they that will not joyn now may hereafter, let every man do as the Lord ſhall perſwade him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 10. and let us do ſo too. This was alwayes the rule and ſaying of one of our beſt friends, In the name of God let us ſee what he ſaith now he is ſtill the ſame man, and for the ſame things we hope though in more power.</p>
            <p>Oh, but you will ſay the people are not yet perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: No, nor never will to any thing for their good; Muſt not we compell men into Chriſt? <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> God muſt perſwade them by his word and Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is the meanes commanded to be uſed, and that that hath been frequently bleſſed, and let that ſatisfie all good men that will be ſatisfied, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 31, <hi>Jud.</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:49710:27"/>
            <p> Yea, the laſt ten yeares experience which you ſay hath filled the world with errors; and although many errours were before concealed, it was but as the weeds are in the night, which are as much then as in the day, onely men cannot ſo well ſee them as when the light ariſes: but God forbid the the Sun ſhould not ſhine for fear of theſe weeds growing or diſcovering.</p>
            <p>The way to weed the world is not to put out the Lights or Light of the world, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 14</p>
            <p>The Devil, errours, ignorance and wickedneſſe may as well hide under a ſhort cote, a rigid Presbyterian ſtrickt and ſtrait Laſt forme as in a Biſhops Goun.</p>
            <p>What think ye of <hi>Scotland</hi> where we be all can Religion for the Kirk and Pearſon, and in gend faith we will pay the Sectaries Army, and the Devil <hi>Crumwel</hi> the horn of the beaſt, (we ſay of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 6. and we are ſure he was ſo to us, and we hope ever will be) What? Stand againſt the Kirk of God, Preach themſelves, and ſpeak againſt their Miniſters; aut, aut, for ſhame, haang theſe heretick dogs, falſe lowns and blaſphemers, yea, the curſe of God and the holy Kirk light on them all I ſay.</p>
            <p>What do you think of theſe poor ſimple ignorant and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched people, which never wanted legall Preachers; but alas, is their harveſt like ours, or is there not too too much want of our gifted Saints amongſt them, the Lord convince all oppoſers upon this conſideration, and the experience from among our ſelves, for although more errours may be now then ten or twelve yeares ago, yet we are ſure they are not conſiderable to the numberleſſe number of knowers that are more now than ever in <hi>England,</hi> yea, in any place of the world, and we hope ye fear egransdamnes a thouſand for one hundred, and I pray conſider that.</p>
            <p>But we conclude with this Prayer, The Lord grant our knowledge lay none of us the more low in hell; and on the other hand lead ſome, that ſee and will not, towards the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, which of all men in the world clear knowers, ſtrict Profeſſors and rigid men are apteſt to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49710:28"/> fall into; we have told you already who alwayes reſiſted the holy Ghoſt, and murdered the Lord of life and glory; O if ever a Prophet periſh in <hi>England,</hi> it will be by <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem:</hi> meanes, the knowing legal godly men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 33, 34, 35.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>An Exhortation to the gifted Saints to manage well this Liberty, or ſome Goſpel Rules for new Preachers.</head>
            <p>ANd now holy brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, joys, gifts and graces of the holy Spirit, which few or none of the Princes of this world which come to nought do or have known for many hundred years, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6. yet not hid from ſome of the Princes of this world now in our dayes, the glory of the Nation, and to you we would be free, for we are all ſo being the Lords bond men and ſervants, yea, to ſome of you in great Authority, we cannot but commend it if we could, we would certainly command it, but do for the preſent on the knees of our affections humbly intreat you to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to this mean, high and low work, the work of a few Fiſhers at the firſt, God himſelf in Perſon after, though at firſt of all by many great men, Kings, Prieſts, Prophets, <hi>Samuel, Moſes, Aaron, David</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> now <hi>Peter Paul, James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> again, yet not without the old Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the Spirit of his Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God, who at ſundry times, and in diverſe manners ſpake in times past by the fathers the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt times ſpoken to us by his Son, Heb.</hi> 1. 1.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49710:28"/>
            <p> You the great Saints of <hi>England,</hi> and glory of the world, we would intreat you on the knee again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, yea, beſeech you in the bowels of love, yea, the God of love, and the mercies of that God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2 for his own, and the honour of his, and the poor gifted Saints ſake, that you would all pull off your Crowns of honour for an hour, as once the poor fiſhers did their great bootes to follow Chriſt, elſe it would have been but ſlow.</p>
            <p>And you my Lord Protector; What if you ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in this high and low work, and give us in your own Perſon one ſhort and ſweet Sermon now at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> as late you did to your own Family, we would ſay King <hi>David</hi> were on earth again, and put in their murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more at your preſent greatneſſe, who did a meaner thing in dancing before the Ark of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 16. My Lord, look to the Canopies above, and down again to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> yea, your ſelf, and what are you (though ſo great a Saint) more than a worm, gnat, nothing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. 14. Yet may you Nothing, this way honour him that is what he is, and doth what he pleaſes in heaven and in earth, yea, in hell, amongſt and with Saints, Angels, men and divels, yea, every li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thing, as well things that are not, winds, Seas, ſtorm, fire, hail, ice, ſnow, yea, day and night, for they are all his too, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 16.</p>
            <p>This one Being, and Being of all Beings may you poor Nothing yet preach, and our good Lord Jeſus, who once beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e nothing to ſerve and make you and us all Kings, Prieſts and Prophets to our God by his blood. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
            <p>Not that above once or twice we deſire this work of honour from and for you to preach this God that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very moment rides the circle of the heavens, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 22. upon the mighty wings and Chariots of the windes that drawes or drives the cloud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hither and thither, yea, the Seas, where he wills quite from off the earth, and flings
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49710:29"/> them down again upon the Prayers of his people, when and where he pleaſe, as lately now, when man and beaſt was mourning, yea, every ſenſleſſe creature dying, yea, the earth it ſelf yauning wide, as if that and all would dye, yea, dye they would, and dye they muſt at once, but God prevented all for his peoples ſake, and ſaid live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh that men would praiſe his Name, and ſing again his mercy endureth for ever, Pſal.</hi> 136. a Pſalm for your ſoul in ſecret, but a Sermon it is we beg, yea, one at at leaſt from you my Lord, and the Princes among the people, yea the Saints of the moſt high God, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 27 ſhall imitate you all for the honour of the work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nathaniel Pickering, Wooſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, Sadler,</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> all which and many more could and can, pray and Preach bravelie; and if all <hi>Jacob</hi> be but one worm to the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> 'tis no diſhonour to theſe choice bitts of this worm to praiſe their Maker once or twice at the leaſt in the great Congregations, and the Aſſemblies of the Saints, which <hi>David</hi> hints ſo often at, as his own practice in a ſoul exalting way of glorie, <hi>I will praiſe thee in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, yea, in the great Congregation of the people, yea, among the Gods, Pſal.</hi> 111. 1. and 138. 1.</p>
            <p>I will do it, and will not you Gods your ſelves once at the Prayers of all Saints, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in another caſe, God forbid you or any ſhould be aſhamed of a good Maſter, and what is it elſe that ſome princes ſtick at; Come, come, it will be an honour one day to come bowing to the Saints, and lick the duſt of their feet, yea, the meaneſt work for Chriſt, and them, will be an honour for the greateſt Monarchs in the world, yea, to preach this King of kings, that hath this Name written on his thigh, <hi>The Word of God, Rev</hi> 19. 13. and 16. Read ye often the ſixtie of <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> but let us come down from theſe gods to the people, yea, to the Saints that may tend it beſt, and moſt to them we have a word.</p>
            <p>Be as the tree or river in the Paradiſe of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49710:29"/> 7. Watering and feeding, yea, feed and water, yea, that have gifts, all the reſt, yea, all the Church of God over which you are made in your own proper places Overſeers, a high glory ſo to be <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28. but begin at the 17. verſe, and mark well the whole Chapter.</p>
            <p>The Angels never were but ſervants to bring newes or carry Saints to their home, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14. and how ſweetly did they ſing for joy of this glorying in the Work, <hi>Luk.</hi> 29. And what may you ſay? Oh yee duſt of <hi>Jacob</hi> who are all of you together leſſe then the leaſt of the mercies of a God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. 10.</p>
            <p>Your God we mean, and your work we are at, that is to Preach him up, ſin, Satan, death and Devils down; yea, to their own places, I mean the ſorrowes of the Saints, and the works of darkneſſe, all which are to be Preached down, and Chriſt up, from the grave of death and hell, with the keyes of both in his hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
            <p>This Lord and theſe keyes muſt you Preach up, yea, the power now in his hand, and in his hand alone, over ſin, Satan, curſe, grave, Law, men, devils, Saints and Angels, things preſent and to come, yea, over all theſe he is King for ever, and hath wholly and ſolely the power of, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver theſe things, ſouls and conſciences of men. That is one thing my Brethren, you are now called to Preach up, by the firſt born, which do call on you from the riſing of the light, life and love of God now in their ſouls, and therefore do not ſcruple.</p>
            <p>Oh ye Kings of the Eaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 12. but come forth as the morning Sun in the glory of your gifts and graces, and the Spirit of the Son and Father, and Preach up all three, the Father in his love, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. the Son in his merit, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 18. yea and the fruits, joyes, life and power of the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22. converting and convincing, killing, ſaving, damning and deſtroying powers, burning up, and burning down like devouring fire in and on the ſoul, the world and all the works of fleſh, flaming up to the heavens, the righteouſneſſe of men, much more pride, hypocr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſie,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49710:30"/> ſelf, and the fooliſhneſſe of and in man, every whereas he turns from one form to another, reſting more than he ought therein.</p>
            <p>Well, and who is now free, fit and ſufficient for this thing, but our ſufficiency is of God, 2 Cor. 3. 5. And he hath appointed for good men every one to contribute what he hath, and yet I know my brethren you have juſt nothing of your own but a little ſelf-pride, and ſelf-covetouſneſſe, earthlineſſe and luſt, anger, pride, malice, emptineſſe, and fulneſſe in your own conceit, yea, this is all the beſt of you all have; Are not ye ſtufft with theſe things hatred and rebuke, yea, your very hearts as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes in another ſenſe, and would be ſeen of men as Chriſt tells elſewhere, being very hypocrites, pray, preach, diſpute and Propheſie for nothing elſe in the world but to get the world, becauſe it is a ſtep and ſtirrup for preferment to be ſeen of men ſo to do, and glory to the fleſh to be counted ſomebody, and a brave Preacher, yea, almoſt a Paſtor at leaſt a Member and an Officer in the Church of Chriſt, called ſuch a mans Church, an ungodly diveliſh word; Who hath a Church but Chriſt? What? hath every ſelfiſh Saint a Church purchaſed by his own blood, got and brought from the body, I know not how? No, it may be never of it, but got into it at a back door, or brought in head and ſhoulders, or for company, which is beſt ſtill in the beſt things; But this is ſtark nought to call any Church of Chriſt, or little peece of his body by the name of this or that, or t'other man; but be ye what ye will, Paſtor, Preacher, Church or no Church.</p>
            <p>Minde what you are in your ſelves, though in Chriſt we all know you are righteous, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 10. Yea, you eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that are gifted Saints indeed, for our eye is ſtill on you, and onely you for carrying on this work of Reformation in the world, and ſetting up of Chriſt in the Popes Chair, as it were, and if ever he had a pill or a pull, this will be one to purpoſe, yea, me thinks we ſee the Rope juſt about his neck himſelf hanged up and choaked, and the Spirit breathing,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49710:30"/> yea, the witneſſes which have lyen dead and ſlain as it were many hundred years, or Propheſying in ſackcloath at the beſt are now alive again; do not you hear and ſee them ſpeak, pray, Preach and Propheſie and their beds green <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 16. Fruitfull in their Work, ſucceſſefull in their warre againſt ſin, Satan, Turk, Pope, divel, divels mates, and all the powers of hell, Munks, Punks, Prieſts Fryars, whoriſh and falſe worſhippers, theſe rogues, rovers, drovers robbers of the ſoul of men, backs and bellies too, Pigmongers, whoormongers, Applemongers, Egg, Corn, Peaſe or Baconmongers, loving all and better bitts too: greedy doggs, and Prieſts that can never bark, pray nor preach, but are ſnapping honeſt men in all hours and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, often on the Ale bench, Puffe and tipling elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, but the witneſſes are up on their leggs again, for the King of glory as in the dayes of old.</p>
            <p>And have at, away runs the rabble, the Kings of the Eall drive theſe locuſts to the Weſt, the Divels to their dens, and Imps to their dams, and Errors to their homes. yea, all to the Divell, moſt to the Pope, many to the Maſs-Prieſt, t'other Prieſt too, and his tail, luſtfull, lazy, idle, ſimple, ignorant, wanton, looſe, and vain-glorlous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Shakers, Quakers, and ungodly Ranters, ſome ſuch there be.</p>
            <p>All theſe, and your journey Jobbers, hard red faced Clerks, Sawers, Pſalm-men, Wardens, Pares, neither good, drunken Readers, Sleepers, Runners, or Baptizers, that have alwayes Croſſe and Common prayer, yea, and Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their Pockets too; theſe are all the long tail of the Prieſt, where theſe errors, like a bag full of catterpillars, hang as on an old buſh, the riſing of theſe Kings, Tub-Preachers ſo call'd, fires, frights, yea, burnes bag, buſh, yea, the divels neſt and all; And this is your work, mark how <hi>Pauls</hi> fals, the ſcaffold to the Body, all to the ground. It is our work, and it doth us good to the heart to ſee how the old idle whoore tumbles, yet hang her, ſhe will make a brave Hoſpital, and a good piece of Reformation it would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49710:31"/> be to give her to the Saints for ſuch a kind of uſe; you that are free, fit, and long for this work, yea, to be ſetting up this new Trade, as ſome fools think, yea, too many good, godly choice, and precious Saints, but take a ſerious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, though a weak application follow, the Jews Temple rent, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 51. at the ſlaying Chriſt, in that was the true worſhip, and true worſhippers of God, but the worſhip and worſhippers were little leſſe then a den of thieves and robbers, yea they murdered the Lord of life and glory, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 52. God teares their worſhip, yea, the worſhippers in pieces, rejecting both by this ſimile, rending the whole Temple in twain, yea, did he ever ſince ſmile on that ſinfull ſelfiſh people againſt the appearances of Chriſt in his own Perſon, and Diſciples whom he ever, did and doth ſtill love as himſelf, but theſe zealots in their darkneſſe doth by the ſervant, as before with the Maſter, one is a Belzebub, yea, ſo ſaith the Scribes, Phariſees and Doctors, moſt Temple-men, but before this inhumane murther of our Lord Jeſus, the people cryed, <hi>Hoſanna, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna, John</hi> 12. 13. though after <hi>Crucifie, Crucifie, Mark</hi> 15. 13. 14.</p>
            <p>The Prieſt leads the people to their ſin, God rejecteth both, they reject the Stone, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 42. the Stone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the builders, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 15. Yea, the ſacrifice of them all, but the Temple then was rent.</p>
            <p>Mind their ſin throughly, for which this Judgment comes, the Perſon of Chriſt they loathed, the Spirit of Chriſt is as really now in the members of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. As God was in the humane nature of Chriſt when they hang'd him on a tree, this Spirit they cannot come at; but how many this day nail this Spirit, and the appearances of it, yea, the very arms and legs of it, they crown theſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances with reproaches, yea, thornes, ſome think they are making ſuch a cap now, others ſee them ſpit continually in every Sermon. I could almoſt name ſome that cry for the ſpear, noted ones. <hi>(C. A,</hi> and others) what hath this love and ſpeckled Dove done againſt theſe men, which good
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49710:31"/> work is it they would now ſtone him for, is it for enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the world, or filling their hearts with joy, which others did with ſorrow, for convincing men too much of the deeds of darkneſſe, <hi>John</hi> 16. 8. or diſtinguiſhing of the works of holineſſe, wills and inventions of men, all which this Spirit doth, muſt and was to do, yea, to fill the world with Prophets, but take heed ye deſpiſe not theſe little ones, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 6. yea, erring ones, for ſo they are in the eſteem of moſt men.</p>
            <p>Touch not the anointed of the Lord, he hath rebuked Kings for their ſakes, nor do theſe Prophets any harm, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 15. If ever you do, know, God and men fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnes you of medling with theſe or his little Churches, which you are too apt to ſpit at, and ſpeak hardly of, but the work of God is carried on by theſe little trees, ſcattered Saints and Churches, yea, God and his Spirit hath done it.</p>
            <p>And why may not this be a providence or ſign, this piece of <hi>Babels</hi> Temple falling, when a Sparrow fals not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 29. which they ſay hath ſtood ſo many hundred yeares, it is ſtrange, why ſhould it fall now? in the riſing of the Saints, the coming forth of the Spirit, or the zealous perſecuting of the worſhippers; but to receive wounds in our names, holy worſhips, and Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying, as ſchiſmaticks, hereticks, giddie, gaddie, headie, ignorant, factious, fooliſh, and blaſphemous men, oppoſers of all government, and all for our holy worſhip, as we think from God, and according to the mind of God, yea for all theſe wounds in the houſes of our friends, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13. 6. this wounds our ſoules double as it were.</p>
            <p>This preſent Simile and fall may prognoſticate ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, our prayer and prayers ſhall be, that you nor your Temple may never be left to outward judgements, much leſſe your Sacrifice be loathed, or any thing hid from your eyes, yea all our eyes, that may concern your preſent, much more your future weal and happineſſe; yea we will ever pray, that they that ſee may ſay, and they that ſay may ſee,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49710:32"/> what they doe in the day of their viſitation, yea temptation to all that dwell on the earth, or elſewhere, below the true God, life, light, and love of God, and thoſe wherein this light, life, and love is daily manifeſted, which heaven fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward men neither doe nor can know, or did they ever? yet now are fallen, not as the Angels to bondage and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, God forbid, or from the Olive either, the love and ſweetneſſe, life, joyes, and fatneſſe once of communion with the Vine, our head and husbands preſence and embraces, which makes and keeps our beds, and graces, heads, gifts, hearts, joyes and glories lovely, green and fruitful, yea, our bed being ſo by his riſing on, in, and with us, our hearts, joyes, hopes, helps are alwayes near us, nor may, nor can we then be touchie, vain, wanton, ſinful or idle, yea men may ſay what they pleaſe, doe what they pleaſe, tempt while they pleaſe, men and devils all, but we charge you doe not awaken our beloved till he pleaſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 7. yea once again we charge you by the Roes and the Hindes, the leaping of our hearts, the joyes of our ſouls, all which are as in a pleaſant field, a ſpecious and ſpacious place of liberty, where our ſouls are ſported, over hils and dales, high and low, promiſes all chaſed and ſet home upon us by the Spirit, but awake not our beloved untill he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>Yet let us about and about the mountain of ſpices, <hi>Cant,</hi> 8, 14. until the day break, and all theſe ſhadows of ſin, temptations, accuſations and ſorrows flie all away, which for the preſent the body, bed, head, and whole ſoul is filled and laden, ſometimes by friends, who through envie would fain wake our beloved, but ſtill our bed is gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en and fruitful; none of theſe things can cauſe uncleanneſſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean things may, yea do often, come out of mens beds and mouths ſeemingly green like ours: this may and can be, muſt and will be, but can an unclean thing, or action, word, or thought, much more reproach, ſhame, ſinful evil ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, falſe lies and ſlanders, with bitter invectives, the brats of <hi>Babell</hi> begotten with ſtrife, pride, ill-will and envie, on beds of ignorance, ſeemingly green, all baſtards by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49710:32"/> bondage, and the bond-womans ſonnes. But Mount <hi>Sion</hi> the ſonnes of her whoſe beds are green and really ſo, do nor can bring forth any of theſe unclean ſpirits, or the evil of them, love, joy, and the fruits of love, longings, and forbearance, without envie or evil for any, but good will for all, yea and good for evil, the beſt of good we can we wiſh to our enemies, whileſt we pray for our friends, we forget not our ſelves, tis true, nor the worſt of them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the falſeneſſe of them that kiſſe and ſmite us, love us as their lives, and leave us at an hour.</p>
            <p>But we will run on nor off no more from our brethren, onely cloſe up the point, you know what you muſt preach up, and what down, when you go about the work, which the Lord ſet you forward for, and aſſiſt you in.</p>
            <p>Chriſt muſt be preached up in his Kinglie Office, all power in his hands, it may be Church keyes and all, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 22. 22. Yet ſome are too buſie, and claim more than <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ever did, lock out and lock in worſe many times. But ſelf and all of ſelf muſt be preached down, the loves of God, the coming of the Spirit, the Sonnes Merit, and tumbling down of <hi>Pauls,</hi> we mean Gods leaving, of the froward heart and worſhippers, but this latter with abundance of caution, not loudly, nor angerly, or ſeemingly zealous in carriage, or countenance, bitterly, ſo I mean, but with one hand alwayes on your heart in a begging way of conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ever preſſe this point, be ſure to do it, in a love-Dove like winning way, yea, let this holy Spirit breath in you all, and live at reſt in you all, then you muſt be quiet with all men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 18. ſelf, condition and relation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 11. 1 Cor. 6. 7. rather ſuffer wrong, never do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Ier.</hi> 22. 3. You muſt make peace and follow it with and for all men, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
            <p>If you will Preach the God of peace, and our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Prince of peace, <hi>Iſa</hi> 9. 8. hear nor tell no newes that may tend to ſtrife, <hi>Prov.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6 20. Say it is not ſo, ſure you are miſtaken. Ah but he was weak or angry, be ſure you be free from pride and covetouſneſſe the ſin of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49710:33"/> many Preachers, <hi>Prov</hi> 16. 18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. 23. <hi>Luk</hi> 12. 25. Heb. 13. 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 10. do not flye too high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor lye too low in your Preaching, but that I leave till anone, be grave and ſober, 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 14. 40. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 7. be humble and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 13.</p>
            <p>Be ſure you do not Preach, humm, haw, ſpeak little nonſence when you Preach or Pray, yea, and look to the main chance at home, 1 <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> 5. 8. for we will never feed you as a Miniſter, give or lend you ſixpence more than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother brother; it is better to give then to borrow, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 35. have a care of running into debt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 8. ill comming out, theſe cares and thornes will ſpoil any Saint, or Preacher in the world, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 14. Preach ſometimes abroad, yea, be ſure to Preach and pray to and with every one that is ſick, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 14.</p>
            <p>And this you may have leave to do, eſpecially to poor people, and poor Saints, I am afraid may want and want, for all ſome.</p>
            <p>Perſwade all erring, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1. convince all living one time or other, if it were poſſible, remember while ye live this ſaying, Wo be to him that all men ſpeak well of <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 26.</p>
            <p>What good thing doſt thou (Mat. 5. 47.) more then another? And yet a Teacher, a full gut and empty ſtomack alwayes goes together, I am ſure in a Preacher: It is an ugly thing to belch, humm, haw, or ſpit to make thy ſelf to be hemmed up, the ſin of your nothing aſſes; do not be too tedious in Prayer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 7. but pray when you pray, and mind what you ſay, Parrats prate, Papiſts pray, Proteſtants cry, Lord have mercy upon us. Amen. ſay we, for they know not what they ſay many times in the Pew and Pulpit; yea, good men may ſtrive to ſpeak more then in the ſenſe of Gods love or their own vileneſſe; and we are reſolved if you pull a Sermon from your Pocket, we will all run away, therefore keep in the desk if you mean to read old notes or new, we love to drink from the fountain.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49710:33"/>
            <p> Take no notice who governes, confeſſe no more for, nor againſt then is needfull, be ſure ye be not a touchy fool, a Pinch-belly, or a tyrant over ſon or ſervant, nor be too lofty neither, but read often the 6. of the Epheſians, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect moſt for ſinning faults after exhortation, and all kind of Paſſion, Mr. <hi>Dods</hi> rule, have a care of controverſall points, a ripe wit hears, objects, and ſends you home aſhamed after Sermon is done. Never come in flaunting Cuffes, powdred or too long hair, although thou beeſt a gentleman, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 14. Expect not a glaſs of ſack, nor turn into the veſtry that ſtinks of old <hi>Baal</hi> and his veſtments, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 10. 22. but ſlink away home for fear of being proud, ſome body may flatter, have a care of your wifes tongue, much more your own, fooliſh jeſts or laughing, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 16. when you hear them.</p>
            <p>It is enough to be guilty of anothers ſin, a ſilent or mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy look when others laugh is a good reproof: Chriſt never laught at all, no more ſhould a Chriſtian ſcarce, and yet rejoice alwayes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 3. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 16. Yea, this is joy indeed, and not the girning of fools, go by no means to the tipling School, but in ſome great caſes; what? a Parſon in an Alehouſe, more than for a glaſs, it was, is, and ever will be ſcandalous, dine not too much abroad, perſwade thy wife to goſſop ſeldome, the Miniſters wife muſt take place, and ſhe be humble to all, never go too fine; be free, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 13. invite honeſt neighbours now and then to dinner, yea, ſinners, preach Chriſt to them all, that is a Scripture rule, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 15. I am ſure: be not chubbed, dogged, or of a Melancholy look, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. 3. Do for the worſt in the world if thou maiſt without hurt, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially for the Saints, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10. yea, pinch back and belly ſometimes for them, the feet will go far for the head, the head plod much for the belly, the eyes looking after all <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 25. Speak very kind, d'off thy hat to any, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 8. perſwade thy wife not to be too complementall, however love her as Chriſt loved the Church, if ſhe hath a thouſand failings, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 25. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 19. If thou lyeſt,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49710:34"/> cheatſt, or cozeneſt in thy Calling, we will hang thee at thy ſhop, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 21.</p>
            <p>However thou haſt done ſo to thy name and Profeſſion and it ſtinks, do not ſay thou wilt not give and give, ſell and ſell, that's lying, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 14. None will truſt what thou ſaieſt, light gain makes an heavy purſe, and the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a thing in ſome caſes to a poor man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 27. Minde this griping Citizens, go not a ſtargazing, a world gazing, needleſſe walks and viſits, time is precious, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 16. Lords, Ladies, Fools, and young Gallants, yea, too many Chriſtians, ſquander that away.</p>
            <p>If the Sunne be ſetting, or the Sand runne, then they beg and houl, but good Sun, good Sand, or good death, will not hold a minute their immortal ſouls from going to God, Chriſt, joyes, Saints, Angels, Sym, Hym, flames, chaina and devils, one or tother, all men.</p>
            <p>Think on that in time, and be ſure to preach it much to the world, and let not one neighbour forget another ſo ſoon as he hath got his biskets, alwayes think upon the ſoul, and where that is, when the corpes is given to the wormes, yea, and preach a few ſerious points before or after burial, ſingle out two or three, if it be not convenient to the whole, a bodie is dead, a ſoul is gone, and the Kite is coming for another Chick, the Hen makes more ado then ſome for a neer relation, bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord, all the reſt go to the devil, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 14. Read no books but Bibles for thy Sermon, <hi>John</hi> 5. 36. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 11. We ſhall find and loath it, if it be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Do not truſt thy memory, if thou wilt preach, ſtudy, yea, take pains for the gains and joyes of the Spirit, It is reward enough to have ſome Communion, before, in, or after any godly duty. Two or three hours cloſe ſtudying in a day will make thee a brave Preacher; The beſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that we have, do not alwayes beat their brains about the Scriptures, but are ſometimes in the Garden, the world, and governments of the world, yea, in old Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacks,
<pb facs="tcp:49710:34"/> and Fathers too ſome times, but <hi>Timothy</hi> like, give thee thy ſelf wholly to theſt udy of the Bible, that is, let that be the Sum and ſubſtance of thy ſtudy, and to know Chriſt crucified in and for thee, how to preach him to the beſt advantage of a ſoul: now ſuppoſe thou beeſt a Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Gentleman or ſhop-keeper, eſpecially the latter, conſider the day and night conſiſts of twenty four hours; you that Preach, ſeven for the bed is enough in conſcience, one to dreſſe and undreſſe, two for religious duties, if you goe morning night and noon by your ſelves yet it is enough, a brief word of exhortation, and a pithy Prayer is better than a tedious, long and dry buſineſſe, have a care of that in your meetings, ſtrive not to ſpeak beyond the breathings of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Men that have time enough, may inlarge better then he whoſe ſelf and ſervants is too much tyred many times, but Saints ſhould not make their trade a toil, and yet be careful too; four hours in your ſhop beſides your three hours ſtudying, writing Texts and reaſing of the Bibles at one corner of the Counter, and then thou art as ready for a Cuſtomer, as if thou wert gazing up and down, and ſo thy temporall meanes comes in as the Miniſters ſpiritual, in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thy particular Calling, which is rather better bleſt, and lookt too by this kind of practice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> could ſtitch and ſtudy too, or make Tents, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 3. And though in the preſence of the Lord it be far from our deſire for the ſpeciall Miniſters of the Goſpel ſo to do, yet ſtudying &amp; tending of the ſhop, may do well to gather for them that muſt abide in their Callings, and yet we are not out, onely improving time, like good husbands and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteans, we are bid ſo to do, <hi>Eph</hi> 5. 16. and in ſo doing, we are like that diligent hand which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes makes rich; we inrich the Common wealth with the knowledge of Chriſt, and his righteouſneſs by this kind of induſtry, yea, the Miniſters who take the more pains for fear leaſt we ſhould excel them, beſides our experiences are conſiderable, and it will be a good help to them alſo, two may ſee more then
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49710:35"/> one, and two hours more in every day thou may eſt allow thy ſelf to read over debts, gather in and pay, if thine and thy debters names be in one book, 'tis done in half a one, if thy trading be not very great; at this rate eight or nine will be ſpent in thy ſhop, every day take one for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, and that is more then Chriſt took, who was Lord of time and all things: But ſuppoſe thon takeſt two to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create thy ſelf, walk with neighbors, wife and children, Rich Saints, rather poor, crying friend and neighbour what is in the Cubbard, how hangs the taſſles of the buget, we mean how goes things where the charge is great? Is the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord paid? Are ye out of debt, how much will put you in a way of ſubſiſtance?</p>
            <p>All this is good: But ſtay, we muſt not forget the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Gentlemen will have two for that, but we allow, but one for our ſelves, <hi>meat is made for the belly, and the belly for meat,</hi> tis a ſhame how ſome eat, whileſt others faſte, <hi>but God ſhall deſtroy the one and the other,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 13. Yet we have an hour left ſtill, ſpend one halfe of that, and take the reſt to pick up in thy thoughts dead bones and ſculs of thy old acquaintance, yea, go ſpuddel in the grave or cave, brave <hi>Dean</hi> who was ſlid into a vault by his princely Train, and muſick was but a melancholly crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſight, the old board flapt down, the glory all was gone; would ſome would peep in there every day, where they intend to ly, and muſt at laſt, in the mean time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you the worlds vanity, thine own mortality, Chriſts excellency, Heavens joyes, and hels torments, Chriſts coming, and thy dayly going to another world, where thou would be ſtated the firſt moment that thou dieſt in an unchangeable condition; and if it be of glory with Chriſt, as certainly all believers will, yet will their never be an opportunity to act, do or ſpeak one word for this Chriſt or his Saints again as is now, a damned ſinner once in hell will never have a minuts opportunity to do for ſelf, or hear of Chriſt again; nor can a Saint warn a ſinner there; <hi>Laza: us</hi> could not ſend to <hi>Dives</hi> kindred, who, (as it is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49710:35"/> probable) were laughing, playing, buying, ſelling, not at all minding his condition.</p>
            <p>Well, friends if you would be good Preachers, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or forewarners of poor ſimple ſinning ſinners, minde time, ſtudy hard, and reſolve to be, and do to day what you would to morrow if you were to dy, but one Saint of a thouſand is not yet, does not yet, or at leaſt ſo much as he intends, and what a ſad thing is this? How much trouble may it coſt, if death come as a man from a far countrey, or <hi>thief in the night, Rev</hi> 16. 15.</p>
            <p>But to our old rules once again, onely remember this of time, to keep a book or watch to ſee how that goes away, a private book is beſt a thouſand times, and ſet down what of God you injoy, every dayes providence, and what of that is moſt remarkable, tis done in half a quarter of an hour, your failings and diſtempers write down every night, good deeds leave out, Chriſt will tell of them before Men and Angels, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 35. this will be a better glaſſe and a larger, then my Lady fools paint or pleaſure, who is dead while ſhelives, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> for in this you may ſee your life every day and year, and when you ſhall read ſo much communion with God on ſuch a duty, ſuch a ſtrait, ſuch a providence, ſuch a caſualty, or deliverance from the grave, ſelf, wife, or children, ſuch a loſſe, and why ſo? Saints can tell if they pleaſe to look, why every rod comes, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6. 9. and what to doe in a new ſtrait, if they keep the experience of their old deliverance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. 7, 8, 9, 10. the day and year exact, as ſome doe their expences, for ſeven yeares together: the Lord make us as wiſe as the children of this generation, <hi>Luke</hi> 16 8. and eſpecially you that would fain be teachers, which the Lord make you able to; but take one direction for your Bibles, in all your Bibles write us at the ſide, or in every place where there is room for a word, one word and no more; as thus in the ſecond and the third of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> where mention is made of ſeven Churches, and choice promiſes to all: now write, for thy own help and readineſſe, the remarkable word of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49710:36"/> every promiſe in the ſpare places; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thus at the ſeventh verie of the ſecond Chapter, write <hi>Tree;</hi> at the tenth verſe <hi>Crown;</hi> at the ſeventeenth <hi>white Stone; Power,</hi> or <hi>Nation</hi> at the twentie ſeventh: <hi>White Ray</hi> at the fifth verſe of the third Chapter; <hi>Name,</hi> or <hi>Pillar</hi> at the twel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Gold</hi> at the eigthteenth. And ſo in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 13. where the Lord ſaies, <hi>My Servants ſhall eat, but ye ſhall be an hungry, drink, but ye ſhall be thirſty; ſing for joy of heart, but ye ſhall weep and lament.</hi> Set <hi>thirſt, ſing,</hi> or <hi>weep,</hi> at the ſide of the verſe, <hi>bread, water, well, life, treaſure, fulneſſe, rock, refuge, ſtone, lilly, roſe, wine, apple tree, ſhadow, great rock, ſun, ſtar, olive, oyl, prieſt, prophet, King of Kings, Rev.</hi> 19. and 16. Write <hi>thigh, lamb, altar, ſcape goat, ſerpent,</hi> and ſo in regard of Chriſts ſufferings, write <hi>bruſed, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, afflicted,</hi> marred, <hi>ſorrow,</hi> or <hi>a man of ſorrows,</hi> yea, by us a ſixpenny Concordance, or a bigger bound up by it ſelf, and every remarkable word in it, ſet that with your pen by the ſide of the Scripture, eſpecially the moſt uſeful, and where you find one and the ſame remarkable promiſe, or one and the ſame threatning exhortation, or reproof to be in two or three Scriptures, ſet us by the verſe where the remarkable and moſt known word ſtands, a little hint where the other ſtands that is moſt like it, or the ſame.</p>
            <p>Many Bibles have ſomething this way, but you may add much more, and with a little pains make one Bible worth ten of your gaudy ones, and alwayes bring this to the Pulpit, and not a cheating thing like a Bible, gilt, bound, fill'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p and ſtuffed with white Paper, old notes or new, got, ſtole, preacht or borrowed we know not where, nor when, yea it may be ſome ten times over, this is worſe than pinning new leaves in, and truly we think it much our duty to call for it from you, if any of you ſhould do ſo, when you are ſet up; what? rivers of living waters in your belly, <hi>John</hi> 7. 38. and ſpeak by a quill to living ſtones in the Church of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. For ſhame take pains, 'tis lazineſſe and not the memory, 'tis no matter for ſo much, let us have a little life in what we have; and therefore put nothing in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49710:36"/> your Bibles, but here and there a word according to our firſt directions.</p>
            <p>Moſt men will laugh if thou ſpeakeſt fine words, and knoweſt not whence they are derived, much leſſe prate not of the Original, ſome things are hard to be underſtood, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough is, wreſt not the Scripture, a <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16. Speak what thou knoweſt, and know what thou ſpeakeſt; Preach by thy life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 16. In every ten ſhillings that thou geteſt lay by one for the poor, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 11.</p>
            <p>I would to the Lord the Tythes were theirs that have moſt need, the poor Saints, the Church land to the poor ſinners, ſomething would do well, twelvepence every Lords day would do good, and Tradeſmen muſt lay by for the Saints, and one for another every Lords day more or leſſe, what do ye talk of ſixpence, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. Yet a mite is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable.</p>
            <p>Mercy is as good as ſacrifice; I will have that, and not t'other ſaith the Lord, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. 6.</p>
            <p>Many Saints or worldlings as they may be called, will have one, and are much in that, little, little, nothing ſcarce in t'other.</p>
            <p>If a man be worth fifty pound, yea, a crown clear, and will do no good in ſome caſes, he ſhall never feed my ſoul that will not feed my body too in a great diſtreſſe, <hi>James</hi> 2 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John, James, Peter, Paul</hi> would loath ſuch a Preacher yea, lover of the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 13.</p>
            <p>By no meanes preach for or againſt a point that is diſpute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1. eſpecially about Baptizing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 13, 14, 15, 16. mind this Scripture ye great diſputers for it, ſeldome miſſe the Publick, although you do not pray. Preach, or expound, and do that moſt, it is much one and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>What matter whether thou ever goeſt up to the Pulpit?</p>
            <p>Yet ſpeak near it, and not at the other end of the Church.</p>
            <p>If ten be in the Church or Chappel, one may begin with Prayer, and another brother may expound, one or halfe a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49710:37"/> Chapter; but for Chriſt his ſake have a care what ye ſay, you know many thruſt themſelves too forward, ye many times the moſt unfit and unable, learn firſt, then teach but be not ever learning, you might have been good Preachers by this ſaith <hi>Paul, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
            <p>Obſerve that well all ye that oppoſe: When the Miniſter and people are all come, then go no further in Prayer, or rather in expounding.</p>
            <p>Never ſtay for Pſalmmen or Readers, they may all go plough, play, or ſing <hi>Te Deum,</hi> and yet we are for both in the Publick places; but why ſhould any but a godly man do either, we think St. <hi>Paul</hi> had no ſuch Clarks, and readers as too many have; yea, we think there muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as great a call for either as for Preaching, yet the worſt may touch the Ark here, though they fill the pot and pipe all the week beſides, but not a godly grave and ſober Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian by no meanes, able to preach pray and expound ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Spirit, would ſome of you would prove theſe mens Callings, before you diſprove ours, which reaſon God and nature ſeems to allow.</p>
            <p>Doth the roſe ſend forth its ſweetneſſe, the vine and olive too their fatneſſe, and are we to make the moſt good of every good thing? but the gifts of Gods Spirit muſt ly ſtill, or hid as in a napkin, and yet the Bee carries all her honey to the hive; but we muſt carry nothing to the Church of Chriſt, though we labour for it as the Miniſters do, yea, fetch it from the ſame flowers and promiſes, ſo that it is juſt the ſame thing we bring, and by the ſame Spirit, but we are cloathed in gray, yea, in fools cotes many times, and made the ſcorn of the world, for bringing honey to the hive: Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God doth nothing in vain, yea, every thing for the moſt advantage, he gives the rain, not for the earths ſake alone, but for man and beaſt, gifts and parts ſeems to us to be given for ſome ſuch publick end, elſe why are we bid in a generall way ſo earneſtly to covet for it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14, 1.</p>
            <p>Meditation is as good as Preaching for a mans ſelf, yet covet to propheſie, to your Family ſayeth the Miniſter, one
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49710:37"/> neighbour or two, then ſay we it is as lawfull if a hundred comes, and more publick too then theirs, if there he but ninety nine, the People not the Pulpit makes it publick.</p>
            <p>But let us go on with our rules, and keep ſome argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments behinde, parts and Miniſters will turn all, yea, the Moon, ſome ſay, to green Cheaſe, yea, and this Sun to darkneſſe too, if men will believe all that ſome of them ſay, but obſerve well their end that ſhall bitterly write or preach againſt this truth; yea, ſee if theſe men dy the common death of other Saints, which is to be moſt fruitfull in their old age, like <hi>Davids</hi> tree, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 6. But we fear theſe men will be like the figtree, the broken bough, or fallen leaf underneath the tree, or high way ſide, yea, if they do not weather, God hath not ſpoken by us; have not we obſerved? <hi>Be ſilent O earth, God is riſen out of his holy place, Zach.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>And the blaſt of the terrible One ſhall light upon them, Iſa.</hi> 25. 4.</p>
            <p>Well, but if any be free to ſtay longer than the Miniſter hath done, then exerciſe again, when the reſt are all gone out <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 15. If it be poſſible let three or four gifted Chriſtians keep a meeting up in every publick place, as now they do in a Parler which is too private, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 27. to begin and end juſt at an hour, and alwayes give a little bread or ſomething to the poor of the Pariſh, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 2. One rich Saint may do that for the honour of all, and never hurt himſelf; this may toll in poor men and beggers unto Chriſt, whoſe ſouls are as precious as the Kings of Nations, and more to be pitied too, for their poverty and ignorance, yet both more worth then a thouſand worlds, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 26. Get the Miniſter as often as may be to be with you, not to ſpeak by no meanes, they will eat up time too much; Minde this gathered Saints and Churches, moſt of your Paſtors are very guilty this way, and I pray God there be not a popes toe in this alſo; why ſhould one have almoſt all the time? Let them keep and ſee it beſt managed, how their flock and people thrive, and what light and life is amongſt them, this will guid and help them
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49710:38"/> all in Preaching, knit and tye hearts and hearts together.</p>
            <p>More might be added, as the ſending of your gifted Saints ten, twenty, thirty miles, for a moneth more or leſſe, <hi>Phit.</hi> 2. 19, 25.</p>
            <p>If he be free and well able to defraud his charge, elſe the friends of Chriſt muſt do it for him, the rich contributing double and treble; who can ſpend means better, and let ever ſome of theſe true travellers of and for Sion be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling to one place or another, Preaching to, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after Saints, and their walkings all along the rode, alighting ſtill to viſite every ſick and afflicted one.</p>
            <p>This will be as a Meſſenger of a thouſand, did a brother ſo come, to a Saint ſick or dying he would be received as an Angel of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in another caſe, what? a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger from the Saints, ten twenty or thirty miles to viſite me, like <hi>Sion</hi> whom no man regarded, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 17.</p>
            <p>For my poverty or weakneſſe ſurely the Lord alone ſent him, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid to his brethren, but never take this journy without the State gifted Brethren Saints, and as many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians hands as may conveniently be got of the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, yea, the Miniſters if it can be got, and half a dozen of honeſt men going to him may do much, if he be a good one, elſe take it not by no means; and let this with a godly Juſtice be by the States order to impower you to command the keyes in any place Church or Chapel now in <hi>England,</hi> in caſe the Miniſters or Church-wardens be malignantly oppoſite; and upon their and the Conſtables perill let it be if any ſhould be wronged going ſo forth: And this is the main work of all we would be at, and not ſo much preach where there is little need, unleſſe it be to improve our time and talents, yea, never where there is an able Miniſter but a little before he comes, and after, and yet we would have a care of tyring men too much; a ſix a clock Lector may do well in any mans Church in the Summer mornings, <hi>John</hi> 8. 1, and 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63. 2. and perſwade the Miniſter to come or ſend his ſervants rather, he himſelf may be buſie
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49710:38"/> in his ſtudy, and let all conſider if want be within three or four miles off <hi>London,</hi> ſome Chappels quite ſhut up, others none but Maſſe Prieſts, Common-prayer men, that can preach and pray no more than a cat to any purpoſe to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them; what want then muſt needs be twenty miles round, well, you ſee your work, we your willingneſſe for the work; The Lord be with one, all and every one of you in your journeys, yea, the mighty God of <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 19. 24. Make you ſtrong againſt all oppoſitions from men or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, yea, the beaſt of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> fought ſo often with, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 32. harmleſſe and wiſe as ſerpents in the managing of your gifts and Liberty, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 16. ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as the primitive Saints, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 46. 47. through the zeal of <hi>Paul,</hi> who became all to all men to gain ſome, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 22. caught and begot many by gile, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 16. beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and beſeeched them to Chriſt by the mercy of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2. to whoſe mercies, loves, armes, joyes and bleſſings, gracious preſence and aſſiſtance we commit you by prayer, and let all be ſent forth ſo and let them follow you, yea, every one of you which are willing to ſpend and be ſpent for Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 15 which none almoſt minds beſides, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 21. O Chriſt how few owns thee in this Nation called by thy Nam? How few lives to thee that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs much, ſweet Jeſus our deereſt dear keep them that do from all enemies as in an Ammunition of rocks, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 10. Let bread be given to them, their work and water never fail, Amen, Amen, Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>IF any unſatisfied man or men without pride, ſelf, or paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would ſeriouſly read ſquier <hi>Shepherds</hi> little book, Called the peoples Priviledge and Duty; guarded againſt the Pulpit and Preachers increachment never anſwer to any purpoſe, but as one Lawyer doth a loſt cauſe, who muſt ſay ſomething to pleaſe his ſimple cliant, who hath fed and feed him all along; yea, a little balling pleaſes ſome when mony and cauſe is both loſt, and it may be ſtill ſome will ſhoot againſt the light of the Spirit, but take heed of looking
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49710:39"/> too much againſt this truth, or thoſe Arrows which ſelf pride, parts, or malice may ſhute upwards at it, but read ſquier <hi>Shepherd</hi> once or twice ſoberly over, you that are willing to be ſatisfied in theſe truths, which doth and ſhall prevail, and now though the ſea rores <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 46. 3, 4.) and makes a noiſe, yet will we be glade, there is a river, the ſtreams thereof ſhall refreſh the City and Citizens of our God, that are now dwelling on mount Sion, and not <hi>Sinai</hi> in <hi>Arabia</hi> the wilderneſſe of ſtrife and bondage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 24, 25, 26.</p>
            <p>And now if the drift of this be erroneous for a wanton Spirit, or againſt our Lord Jeſus, whip us at the cart, or hang us up in chains till we and our names rot, and this is our Petition alſo to you the high and great Councel of theſe Nations; yea, good my Lord, do one or the the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for us, it is the onely way to get our hearts to purpoſe; why ſhould you looſe the choiceſt thing under heaven, next to the heart of God, and we the main fruit of all our tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, blood and treaſure?</p>
            <p>O my Lord, the night comes when none can work, <hi>John</hi> 9 4. Remember that ye ſleepie virgins of <hi>Sion, Awake, awake for our deliverance, O Arm of the Lord, Iſa.</hi> 51. 9, 10. and let all the Churches now in <hi>London,</hi> yea, in <hi>England,</hi> hear what the Spirit ſayes to them <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 29. in this day of their viſitation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:49710:39"/>
            <head>A Hint of ſome Texts we fain would be at, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 11.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E is all and in you all Christ is all in all, in and to himſelf and in the eye of the Father, and working of the Spirit; he is all and in all to his Saints, the laſt and preſent help and hope of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ners he is the light, life and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory of the world, the image of the Father; the Son, Rock, Well, Water, Spring, Morning Star, light, life and comfort of the Saints; all in all to them in his Names and Titles, ſweet Jeſus, Lord Jeſus, anointed Chriſt, God-Man, Man-God, Immanuel with and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n us, Titles, King of, for, and in the Saints, to keep, ſave, help and deliver all Believers, from, ſin, death, hell, flames, men, divels, dangers, grave, ſting, curſe and curſes, Law, fears, bondage and captivity, yea, a Prieſt to pray day and night, he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds continually when we do, and cannot at the Throne of grace; if we live die or ſin he is ſtill our interceſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to us when we pray, preach, study, minde, think or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate; that is ſweet, heaven comes down, ſoul goes up, world laid by, we dye, live and contemplate our God, but Chriſt is all in all, in health, ſickneſſe, wealth, plenty, want, poverty, all caſes, of all kindes, whatſoever, yea, in life, and death, Christ is all, and he that hath him ſhall not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dye, nor lye long in the grave, <hi>John</hi> 11. 26. and it is dead whilſt he lives, and ſhall live when he dyes, with, to, and before the throne of God and the Lamb, ſinging glory, praiſe, honour and ſalvation, Palmleaves, white Robes, throng of Angels, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 9. Wicked men dying ſo, curſe, gnaw, cry, houl tear, damn, roar with, in and among, brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, pitch, roſin, worm, conſcience, ſatire, ſcrich owle, divels fighting, flying, teeth gnaſhing, damned ſouls cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, altogether frying, for refuſing Chriſt who is all in all, little pleaſure, profit, ſtories, va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n glories, crownes, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, names, fames, capps, knees, bowings, melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſick, joyes, toyes, moments pleaſure, earthly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49710:40"/> ſweet meat, ſoure ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: What is all to he, and and what is he to nothing? t'other nothing gets nothing, loſes all for nothing. Oh Chriſt be my portion; what will all avail me when I come to dye, or a little thatch, he whoſe goods, wife, children are all burnt by a fire, their welfare thee leſſe if thy ſoul miſearry for want of this All.</p>
            <p>This and theſe Texts we fain would be at.</p>
            <p>Behold the Lamb of God that takes away the ſins of the world, <hi>John</hi> 1. 29. If ye be riſen with Christ, ſeek thoſe things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth on the right hand of God. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 3, 4. And when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, then ſhall we alſo appear with him in glory: Jud. 20, buy of me gold tryed in the fire, that thou mayeſt be rich, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3 18. Build up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re another in your most holy faith, what ſhall it profite a man to gain the world and looſe his own ſoul? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 26. I ſleep but my heart wakes, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5 2. Bear you one anothers burdens, and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 2. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſſe a man be born again he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee the Kingdom of God, <hi>John</hi> 3. 3. The night comes when none can work, <hi>John</hi> 9. 3. Speak not evill of dignities <hi>Jud.</hi> 8. Wo be to you when all men ſpeak well of you, Luk. 6. 26. Every man ſeeks his own things, but none the things of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 21. Thy loving kindneſſe is better then life, therefore my lips ſhall praiſe thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63. 3. God is love, and they that dwell in God dwell in love, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4 16 I have fought the good ſlght, I have finiſhed my courſe, henceforth is laid up for me a crown of glory, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7. If any man draw back my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 38. Yet when ye have done all ſay ye are unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſervants, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. 10. I am come into my garden my ſiſter my ſpouſe. Amen, even ſo come Lord Jeſus, Can. 5. 1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 20. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Texts and no other by the grace of God, would we Preach and ſtudy: but if curſed be the man that doth the deſtroying work of God negligently, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48. 10. much more he that hinders this wilfully: but we are ready not onely to be bound, but to dye for Christ at Jeruſalem, yea, welcome all for him, <hi>Acts</hi> 21 13.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
